<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands iustification for her religion Wherein it is maintayned to be the same our Saviour Iesus Christ hath taught us. Presented to the high court of Parliament. By a well-wisher of peace in the Church, and happinesse to the Kingdome.</title>
            <author>Well-wisher of peace in the Church, and happinesse to the Kingdome.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38405</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2991</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218201</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829812</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829812</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34256</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38405)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34256)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2026:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands iustification for her religion Wherein it is maintayned to be the same our Saviour Iesus Christ hath taught us. Presented to the high court of Parliament. By a well-wisher of peace in the Church, and happinesse to the Kingdome.</title>
                  <author>Well-wisher of peace in the Church, and happinesse to the Kingdome.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 reads: A iustification of the religion now professed in England.</note>
                  <note>Gathered in 4's.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]²  B-L⁴.</note>
                  <note>Cropped at head affecting title, running titles and page numbers; some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34256:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS IVSTIFICATION FOR HER RELIGION.</p>
            <p>Wherein it is maintayned to be the ſame our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt hath taught us.</p>
            <p>Preſented to the High Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>By a Well-wiſher of Peace in the Church, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Kingdome.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts. 24.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>This I profeſſe unto thee, that according to the way which they call Hereſie, ſo doe I ſerve the God of my Fathers, beleeving all things which hath beene written in the Law, and in the Prophets.</p>
               <bibl>Vigilius <hi>againſt</hi> Euryches: lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>This is the Catholique Faith and Profeſſion which the Apoſtles have delivered, which the Martyrs have confirmed, and which the Faithfull preſerve even to this preſent age.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:34256:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34256:2"/>
            <head>The Contents of the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Chapters of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hap. 1. <hi>The ſumme of our Religion profeſſed in</hi> England. pag. 1.</item>
               <item>Chap. 2. <hi>The particulars of our Religion profeſſed in</hi> England. pag. 3.</item>
               <item>Chap. 3. <hi>Diuine Seruice is to bee admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in a language which the people vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</hi> pag. 18.</item>
               <item>Chap. 4. <hi>Of the reading and expounding to the people, the word of God, and not the Legends and Fables of men.</hi> pag. 29.</item>
               <item>Chap. 5. <hi>Of Preaching.</hi> pag. 35.</item>
               <item>Chap. 6. <hi>Of Sacraments.</hi> pag. 41.</item>
               <item>Chap. 7. <hi>Of Baptiſme.</hi> pag. 43.</item>
               <item>Chap. 8. <hi>Of the Lords Supper.</hi> pag. 44.</item>
               <item>Chap. 9. <hi>Of Prayer.</hi> pag. 56.</item>
               <item>Chap. 10. <hi>Of Martyrs.</hi> pag. 68.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34256:3"/>
            <head>The vvriting occaſioning this Treatiſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Deſire to haue it proued, that the Religion now profeſſed in <hi>England</hi> is the ſame which our Sauiour Chriſt taught his Apoſtles, and they preached ouer all they world, and conuerted thouſands at one Sermon vnto.</p>
            <p>Jf it be the ſame, then there may bee ſome named that ſuffered for it: For it is not likely that ſo many thouſands which were conuerted to the true Faith ſhould all be deſtroyed, and no mention made of them in ancient Hiſtories.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:34256:3"/>
            <head>A IVSTIFICATION OF THE RELIGION NOW PROFESSED IN ENGLAND.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The ſumme of our Religion profeſſed in England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O proue that is here deſired, had beene ſooner done, if the matter had concerned onely ſome particular poynts of our Religion profeſſed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,;</hi> but now the proofe required being general with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any limitation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and extending it ſelfe to our whole Religion, it muſt firſt bee ſhewed what Religion we profeſſe; and then ſuch proofe is to bee made of the ſame as is here demanded, both ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and in ſome principall parts thereof: Firſt, that our Sauiour and his Apoſtles taught the ſame; then that the Martyrs mentioned in ancient Hiſtories gaue teſtimony to the ſame by their death.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:34256:4"/>
               <p> For clearing of the former point, it is here to bee vnderſtood,
<note place="margin">Acts 24.14.</note> Firſt, that Religion is the way and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate duety whereby men ſerue God: And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that true Religion and the right way to ſerue G d, is that onely which God hath reuealed to men. Now God ſpake to the Fathers in old time by the Prophets, declaring his will herein by peece-meale or by ſundry parts, and in ſundry manners; <hi>but in theſe laſt dayes</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>he hath ſpoken to vs by his Sonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1.1.</note> that is, by Ieſus Chriſt. In which words the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the oppoſition of theſe two reuelations of the will of God, declareth that by Ieſus Chriſt his onely Sonne, God hath reuealed his will concerning true Religion, and the right way to worſhippe and ſerue him, not any more by parts, but wholly and fully, nor in any manner that may be after changed, as was the worſhip of the Fathers, but in a manner certaine, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, and to remaine for euer.</p>
               <p>This Religion our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt firſt taught in his owne ſacred perſon, as it is declared in the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Goſpell written by foure witneſſes, two Apoſtles and two Euangeliſts: after by his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, his holy Apoſtles preached and publiſhed the ſame Religion to all Nations. For the preaching whereof vnto them while they yet remained at <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 1.5, 8.</note> according to his promiſe they were baptized with the holy Ghoſt and with fire. By which holy Spirits inſpiration,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.3, 4.</note> they being clothed with power from aboue, and hauing receiued the miraculous gift to ſpeake with ſtrange languages, and a mighty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all ſpirituall graces needfull for that ſeruice, ſo ſpake of the great workes of God to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that from all parts of the world were come to <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:34256:4"/>that the ſame day there were added to the Church about 3000. perſons.
<note place="margin">Acts 2.4.1.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 8.1.</note> After by reaſon of the perſecution that was raiſed againſt thoſe that receiued their doctrine, and other occaſions that God diſpoſed, their doctrine was publiſhed in diuerſe Countries;
<note place="margin">Acts 11.26.</note> and at <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Syria</hi> ſo preuailed, that there firſt the Diſciples were na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Chriſtians, of Chriſt whoſe Religion they receiued; of which beginning and proceeding of the Goſpell, to the time of the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> impriſonment at <hi>Rome,</hi> the Euangeliſt <hi>Luke</hi> hath written the vndoubted certainty in his hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, which ſtory is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged by that was written alſo hereof by ſome of the Apoſtles themſelues in their Epiſtles, and alſo in the <hi>Reuelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which ſacred bookes of the new Teſtament, it moſt certainly and manifeſtly appeareth what the religion and doctrine was which our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught, and Chriſtian Churches af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter profeſſed that continued in their doctrine: And this is ſummarily that moſt holy faith and true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion which is now profeſſed in <hi>England,</hi> and eſtabliſhed by publique Authority. Thus ſummari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwers is made to that is here deſired.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The particulars of our Religion profeſſed in England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow for further ſatisfaction in the particular points of our Religion now profeſſed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> it is to be vnderſtood that there are two bookes eſtabliſhed by publique and higheſt authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34256:5"/>amongſt vs, wherein are declared the particular points of Chriſtian Religion, as they now are recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and profeſſed in <hi>England;</hi> the one of theſe is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled the booke of Articles of Chriſtian Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed in the Conuocation, in the yeere of our Lord 1562. In which booke is declared ſhortly in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Articles, the whole doctrine of Faith, and of the Sacraments which we profeſſe.</p>
               <p>The other is the booke of diuine Seruice and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, wherein is ſet downe the whole order whereby we ſerue God publiquely in our Churches. In theſe two, or in either of them (for ſubſtance) is contained the declaration of our Religion: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the Religion deliuered in either of theſe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e prooued to bee the ſame which Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught, and that which for any part whereof true Martyrs of ancient time haue ſuffered, then is that prooued which is here deſired, which proofe at this time it ſeemeth moſt conuenient to be made, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the booke of diuine Seruice. For the Law with vs requireth eſpecially to ſerue God, according to ſuch forme as is eſtabliſhed by Authority, and ſet downe in the booke of diuine Seruice and common Prayer. Therefore to yeeld ſatisfaction to ſuch Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Catholique Recuſants as are offended at ſuch parts thereof as differ from the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſuch principall parts of the ſaid diuine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice are here to bee iuſtified to bee eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs according to that Doctrine which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles haue deliuered.</p>
               <p>For performance whereof, it is to be vnderſtood, that there are ſundry points of Religion ſet downe in the ſaid booke, whereof no pretended Catholique
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34256:5"/>is ſuppoſed to make any doubt: Of this ſort it is that the ſaid Booke appointeth the reading of the holy Scriptures of both the Teſtaments, and particularly out of the old Teſtament, of the Law of the two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles contayning the ten Commandements of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God; and out of the new Teſtament, of the Lords Prayer. Of like kinde alſo it is that in the ſame, our faith in many of the higheſt and moſt ſacred my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Chriſtian Religion, is declared and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in three of the moſt ancient and notable Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſtian faith that haue beene gathered out of the Scriptures in any former ages: Of which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions or Creedes as they are commonly called, the firſt and moſt ancient is that which vſually is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Apoſtles Creede, becauſe it containeth many principall points of the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, and in a great part, followeth from one degree to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other the Story of the Goſpell, concerning the ſundry degrees of the humiliation and glory of our Sauiour Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The other two, are ſomewhat larger declarations of the ſame points of doctrine that are in the former; of which Confeſſions or Creedes, the one is of <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> that reſolute &amp; conſtant Profeſſor of Chriſt, worthy in honour to be immortall in the Church ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his name.</p>
               <p>The other, the Creede ſet forth by the firſt and moſt famous <hi>oecumenicall</hi> Councell of <hi>Nice:</hi> Beſides theſe, though not expreſſed in this booke, the Lawes of <hi>England</hi> ſo receiue the holy determinations of all the firſt foure generall Councels, in that they agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to the Scriptures determined of the doctrine concerning Chriſts two natures, of God and Man;
<pb facs="tcp:34256:6"/>and of the Vnity of his Perſon, and of the Godhead of the holy Ghoſt, againſt the damnable Hereſies of <hi>Arius, Neſtorius, Eutyches,</hi> and <hi>Macedonius,</hi> as they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine puniſhment by death vpon any that ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately maintaine the foreſaid Hereſies.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the ſaid booke appointeth the order for the adminiſtration of both the Sacraments, inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our Sauiour Chriſt, as ſignes and ſeales of the Goſpell of Chriſt and of the righteouſnes that is by Faith; viz. Baptiſme, the Sacrament of our new birth; and the Lords Supper, the Sacrament of our continuall nouriſhment by him to life euerlaſting. Finally the ſame booke containeth (beſides the Lords prayer, the true rule and direction whereby all other are framed) many other godly prayers for all eſtates and degrees, and applied to the confeſſion of our ſins, to the adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other like occaſions of the Church. Thus farre of ſuch particulars as it is to be thought no Chriſtian doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth but that they are from God. Wherefore the proofe to bee made ſeemeth needfull only in ſuch points as our Church hath reformed in the Religion and Liturgie profeſſed and vſed in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now therefore the principall things of difference betweene our diuine S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruice and the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> follow to be conſidered in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parts thereof, after that two points haue beene debated, which are to be regarded in them all; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the former is, the ſubiect or perſon, that is to ſay, who it is that with S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruice of Religion ought to be ſerued and worſhiped by vs:
<note n="*" place="margin">In the Church of <hi>England,</hi> God only is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped with diuine ſeruice; not any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or dead things, as Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, reliques, &amp; ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n like.</note> in <hi>England</hi> by publique Authority, with Diuine ſeruice, the law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth
<pb facs="tcp:34256:6"/>that onely the true eternall God the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty creatour of heauen and earth, and the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, is to be religiouſly ſerued and honored by vs. For which cauſe it is ordained that the word of God be read and expounded, that his Sacraments bee adminiſtred, and that all our prayers be made to God, and to God alone: And by like Authority there are learned Homilies ſet out declaring and prouing that to worſhip creatures in themſelues or in their Images, and to haue them in Churches, is not lawfull. Now in ſome former time by the authority of the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> our Churches &amp; Temples in <hi>England</hi> were wont to bee full of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſome repreſenting God, &amp; the ſacred Myſtery of the Perſons in the Godhead, and ſome repreſenting Ieſus Chriſt, both otherwiſe, and ſpecially as hee was crucified; beſides theſe, there was alſo almoſt an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable multitude of Images repreſenting the Saints departed out of this life, beſides many other, of whoſe Chriſtian vertues there appeared little proofe.</p>
               <p>And as theſe Images were brought into the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſo they were by like authority ſerued and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped, with garments, ornaments, kiſſing, kneeling, creeping, candlelight, cenſing, reading their Legends, finging Anthemes, and making prayers to them, and to their honour, or at leaſt to their honour that were repreſented by them.</p>
               <p>Which being ſo, it is to bee conſidered what our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught concerning the ſubiect of diuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Seruice, that ſo it might appeare that our Religion and manner of ſeruing God in <hi>England,</hi> is the ſame in this reſpect that was taught
<pb facs="tcp:34256:7"/>by them, and that the other of the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to their Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour Chiſt taught that God is a Spirit,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.23, 24.</note> and that whoſoeuer will worſhip him aright, muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in ſpirit and truth: whereby it is plaine that the Godhead or any perſon of the Godhead, cannot be repreſented by an Image. For if no Art of a man, can truely repreſent the ſoule of a man, becauſe it is a ſpirituall ſubſtance which no bodily thing can tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſent, much leſſe can the ſpirituall ſubſtance of God be repreſented, which without all compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is more ſimple.
<note place="margin">Rom. 1. verſe 18. to 24, 25.</note> For which cauſe the Apoſtle ſaith that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> repreſenting God by creatures, were guilty of lying, and turned that which God truely is into a falſe reſemblance. In which reſpect alſo the Prophets call ſuch Images teachers of lyes,
<note place="margin">Hab. 2.18.19 Ier. 10.8.</note> which is manifeſt ſo to be; becauſe it is a falſe repreſentation to repreſent Eternity by that which had a beginning, incorruption by that which is corruptible, the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor by the creature; and that more falſe, then if a man would rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſent the day by the night, light by darkeneſſe, and life by death.</p>
               <p>Moreouer,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.24. to the end.</note> the Apoſtle there teacheth, that God held himſelfe ſo highly diſhonoured thereby, as for that cauſe, he gaue them ouer to their owne luſts to diſhonour themſelves with all kinde of ſhamefull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour and abhominable iniquities.</p>
               <p>Whereunto the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me Apoſtle doth adde in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>that Idolaters ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel 21.8.</note> Likewiſe in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>that Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, together with dogges, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> chanters, Harlots and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſhall not enter into the City of God, the heauenly Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi> Moreouer, our Sauiour Chriſt teacheth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:34256:7"/>the worſhip of God agreeably to the Law, ſaying, it is written.
<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue.</hi> By which words he declareth it to be vtterly vnlawfull to worſhip any creature with the worſhip that is due vnto God; and further that all religious kneeling &amp; adoration is to be yeelded to God onely. Which is agreeable to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient commandement that ſo commandeth God to be worſhipped,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.4.</note> as it forbiddeth by way of Religion &amp; to worſhip with religious worſhip, the likenes of any creature either in heauen or in earth, or in the waters vnder the earth; againſt the tranſgreſſors of which commandement the Lord declareth himſelfe moſt prouoked to vengeance in comparing his anger to the anger of aiealous man, that will not bee pacified by any meanes, but will be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enged vpon the adulterer. Likewiſe in that he addeth further a terrible commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt Idolaters, whom he there declareth to hold for his enemies and ſuch as hate him, in threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to viſite, that is, to puniſh their ſinnes in their children, and alſo in their childrens children to the third and fourth generation.</p>
               <p>For which cauſe the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> exhorteth all Chriſtians to beware of Idols, ſaying,
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 5.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Little children keepe your ſelues from Idols,</hi> or take ye heede and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of Images.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.14</note> So the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writeth to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſaying, <hi>My beloued fly from Idolatry.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.9.</note> Likewiſe the ſame Apoſtle in al his miniſtry ſought to withdraw as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> and the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> ſo all other gentiles from the ſeruice of Idols to ſerue the true God.
<note place="margin">Acts 17.16.</note> For which cauſe alſo being at <hi>Athens</hi> and greiued in ſpirit to ſee their City wholy addicted to the ſeruice of Idols, did moſt zealouſly endeauour
<pb facs="tcp:34256:8"/>both in the Synogogues of the Iewes, and in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place vpon all occaſions, and in the higheſt Court of Iuſtice, to diſſwade them from thoſe vaine and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious ſeruices, and exhort them to worſhip onely the true God the creator of heauen and earth.</p>
               <p>To which end alſo in another place he ſhewing that true Chriſtians (becauſe they are the Temples of God) ought to haue nothing to doe with Idols, ſaith, <hi>What participation hath Iuſtice with iniquitie,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.14.15.</note> or what communion hath light with darkneſſe, or what commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion can Chriſt haue with Belial, or what part can a faithfull man haue with an Infidell, or what agreement can the Temple of God haue with Idols? Wherefore goe yee out from the middeſt of them, and ſeparate your ſelues</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and touch no vncleanc thing, and then I will receiue you, and I will bee your father and you ſhall be my ſonnes and daughters;</hi> ſayth the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. This is that our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught concerning the worſhiping of God only, and the auoyding with all zealous deteſtation the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Idols, and Images, and reliques, and of any creature.</p>
               <p>Now in times paſt, contrary to this doctrine, our Churches were full of Idols and Images, and ſuch religious adoration and ſeruice was yeelded and done vnto them, adoration in bodily geſtures of vncouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the head vnto them, of kiſſing them, and bowing the body and the knee vnto them, and ſuch like ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice; in couering them with garments, adorning them with ornaments, incenſing of them, burning candles before them, beſtowing gifts vpon them, making vowes, and going of Pilgrimages vnto them, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch like ſeruices.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:34256:8"/>
               <p> But the Lord vouchſafing vs mercy, ſtirred vp the ſpirit of our renowned Princes, to reforme ſuch enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, as many vertuous Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> had done the like before them; and hauing cauſed the Temples and Churches to bee cleanſed from all ſuch Idols and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, ſtraightly charged and commanded all their Subiects, abandoning all theſe vaine and moſt impious ſeruices to Idols, to worſhip the true and liuing God, and to yeeld religious adoration and ſeruice to him onely.</p>
               <p>On the contrary, in all places yet ſubiect to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Temples are full of Images, yea pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate houſes, publique ſtreets, and high-wayes, and nothing either ſo priuate or ſo publique, where theſe Idols are not. By which compariſon it manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that our Religion in <hi>England,</hi> for this point of the ſubiect of diuine Seruice, is that which was taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and the ſeruice of the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> is directly contrary to it, and full of Idolatry. But ſome thinke to avoid all that the Scriptures ſpeak againſt Idols and Idolatry by a diſtinction or two; for which end diſtinguiſhing betweene <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they ſay that this latter only, that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to bee giuen to creatures; but the former, that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, may be giuen to ſome creatures, yea &amp; to ſome alſo a higher worſhip which they call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But this diſtinction cannot ſerue to excuſe the worſhip &amp; ſeruice done to Images by ſuch as are ſubiect to the Sea of <hi>Rome:</hi> For the people ignorant of this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (if there were any ſuch in the Scriptures) could not poſſibly be kept from Idolatry by it, but would be in continuall danger to paſſe the bounds of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip preſcribed, and to giue to their Images the honor
<pb facs="tcp:34256:9"/>of Almighty God. But the Scriptures make no ſuch diſtinction at all, but indifferently vſe both theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, to note the ſernice and ſervants of God. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſayth,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye cannot ſerue God and mammon.</hi> Likewiſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calleth himſelfe, <hi>The Seruant of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.1. Gal. 1.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, all the Apoſtles call themſelues by the ſame word, the <hi>Seruants of God.</hi> Of the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> it is ſayd <hi>that they had beene tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to God from Idols,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.29. 1 Theſ. 1.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> to ſerue the true and liuing God;</hi> and in like manner in diuers other places, whereby it is plaine, that this diſtinction hath no ground in the word of God.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, by the ſame word it appeareth that ſuch ſeruices as the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> ordaineth to be done to their Images, are ſuch as are due to God only, and for yeelding whereof to Images, theyr worſhippers are charged with Idolatry. This is proued by that the law ſpeaking of all ſimilitudes of things ſayeth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them nor ſerue them,</hi> And in the firſt booke of the <hi>Kings.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 19.18</note> 19. ver. 18. it is ſayd, <hi>I haue left</hi> 7000. <hi>in Iſrael which haue not bowed the knee to Baal, and whoſe mouth hath not kiſſed him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 11.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Further in the ſecond booke of <hi>Kings,</hi> chap. 18. ver. 14. it is written of the vertuous and zealous King <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekias,</hi> that he tooke away the high places, brake downe the Images, cut downe the groues, and that he beat into powder the braſen Serpent which <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> had made, becauſe the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> to that day had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered incenſe to it, and called it <hi>Nehuſtan,</hi> that is, a peece of braſſe. By which places it appeareth, that for the ſeruices of bowing the knee to the Image of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> and of kiſſing his Image, and of cenſing the braſen
<pb facs="tcp:34256:9"/>Serpent, ſuch worſhippers are reproued as Idolaters. And theſe with many other like are the ſeruices that by the ordinances and practiſe of the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> are dayly done to Images, by thoſe which cleaue ſtill to that Sea; whereof it followeth, that for the ſame cauſes they are iuſtly charged with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry. On the contrary part it appeareth, that our Religion yeelding all religious Seruice onely to the true eternall God, and giuing no ſuch ſeruice to any Image or creature whatſoeuer, is the ſame that was taught by our Sauiour Chriſt and by his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Yet for excuſe of ſuch Idolatry as hath beene men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, there is yet further alleaged, that the Images of the heathen men onely are Idols, and not the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of Chriſtians and holy men ſet vp in the Churches ſubiect to the Sea of <hi>Rome.</hi> But this is plainely confuted by that the Prohibition of the law forbiddeth bowing down of the body, or any manner of religious ſeruice to bee done <hi>to the likenes of any thing is heauen, in the earth,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> or in the waters vnder the earth.</hi> Now the Images ſet vp in all the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Churches, are ſimilitudes of ſome ſuch things, therefore they are by that law forbidden. Beſides, the law commanding God onely to be adored, ſerued, and worſhiped religiouſly, excludeth alike from that honor all creatures whatſoeuer,
<note place="margin">Eſay 42.8.</note> according as it is ſaid <hi>I will not giue my honor to any other:</hi> In regard hereof the Lord making mention of his Iealouſey,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with adult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry that offence done to him in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating ſuch adoration and ſeruice with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Therefore as the wife is no leſſe an adultereſſe, that communicateth the honor and beneuolence due to her husband alone, with the chiefe ſeruant he hath,
<pb facs="tcp:34256:10"/>as the wife of <hi>Potiphar</hi> would haue done with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> then if ſhe yeeld the ſame to a ſtranger: So the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry is no leſſe that is done in communicating theſe honors with the chiefe ſeruants of God, then was the Idolatry of the heathen in yeelding of the ſame to the Lords of the Gentiles. Sometime the Lord in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect compareth himſelfe alſo to a King. Now in like manner they are no leſſe guilty of high treaſon againſt a lawfull King that yeeld his proper regalities and honors to any of his owne ſubiects, then if they did it to ſtrangers. For the alleagiance being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated with any other, high treaſon is commited, whatſoeuer the party be to whom it is yeelded, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be an enemie or a friend, a ſtranger or a ſubiect, one that is farre off, or of the neareſt about him, and of cheefeſt dignity in his Court.</p>
               <p>For theſe are duties that will not admit of any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation and fellowſhip with any other, but are to be yeelded wholly and onely to the ſoueraigne King and lawfull Husband. And as whatſoeuer is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is adultery and high treaſon; ſo in the caſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious adoring and worſhipping, whatſoeuer is yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to any creature, or to the Image and likeneſſe of any creature, is the ſinne of Idolatry. Therefore the difference betwixt the parties repreſented by the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, cannot excuſe the matter. Moreouer, that ſuch adoration and ſeruice is not to be excuſed may appeare, in that often times the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and others, are reprooued for worſhipping the Sunne, the Moone, the Starres, and all the hoſte of heauen. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in that the cenſing of the braſen Serpent is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Idolatry, notwithſtanding that at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it had beene ſet vp by Gods expreſſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb facs="tcp:34256:10"/>for another purpoſe, and that it in a ſort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented Chriſt Crucified, and lifted vp on high by the preaching of the Goſpell, that all which ſhould looke vpon him and behold him with the eye of Faith, might be ſaued from the power and ſting of Sathan the old Serpent.</p>
               <p>The ſame may be alſo prooued by that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 14.14.</note> when they would haue ſacrificed to him (which was no more then offering incenſe to this effect) rent his clothes, and with great zeale deteſted it, that any ſuch thing ſhould be done vnto him. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> alſo being reſpected and reuerenced by <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 10.25, 26.</note> with ſo much reuerence as ſeemed to him might be dangerous to prooue offenſiue to God, withdrew him earneſtly from it, and acknowledged himſelfe to be his fellow ſeruant.</p>
               <p>The worſhip of Angels is likewiſe reprooued in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſsians:</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 2.18.</note> rauiſhed vpon the ſuddaine with admiration of the Angel that had reuealed ſo great Myſteries vnto him, and worſhipping him, was forbidden by the Angell,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 19.10.</note> acknowledging himſelfe to bee fellow ſeruant with <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 22.8, 9.</note> and exhorted to yeeld that honour to God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And if ſuch honour be not to be giuen to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt, nor yet to the Angels in heauen; ſurely it is not to bee giuen to any other creature, much leſſe to their Images.</p>
               <p>Hereunto may be added, that the Images of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, are as well the workemanſhip of men, as thoſe of the Heathen were. Further alſo, that the Images euen of the Apoſtles and of Chriſt himſelfe, were for their matter like to the Images of the Heathen, being made of wood, ſtone, mettall, or ſuch like mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.
<pb facs="tcp:34256:11"/>The outward ſhape alſo is no other. Likewiſe it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to be ſaid as well of them as of the other,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>That they haue eyes to ſee, yet they ſee not; eares to heare, but they heare not; feete to goe, but walke not, but ſtand in neede to be lifted vp to the place where they ſtand, and to be nailed to it leaſt they fall downe;</hi> Therefore no ſuch Images are to bee honoured, nor to bee ſuffered in Chriſtian Churches.</p>
               <p>For theſe and ſuch like are the reaſons for which the worſhippers of Images are reprocued by the Scriptures as Idolaters: <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe they worſhip the workes of mens hands, they worſhip things that are dead, as ſtocks and ſtones, falſe repreſentations, and lying ſhapes, that haue likeneſſe of ſenſes and life, and yet are indued with no ſene nor power of life; and finally, ſuch things as can neither do good nor hurt to men, but need mens helpe to ſtand, and may be burnt or otherwiſe conſumed by them.</p>
               <p>This is the doctrine of our Sauiour Chriſt and of his Apoſtles concerning this point, that God onely is to be religiouſly worſhipped, and that no creatures or their Images are to be adored. After that alſo a long time, the ſame doctrine was acknowledged, and the worſhip of Images reprooued. For declaring whereof it may ſuffice here to ſet downe that which is reported by <hi>Epiphanius</hi> himſelfe, and is tranſlated by <hi>Ierome. Epiphanius</hi> in his letter to <hi>Iohn</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> writeth hereof in this manner: I found in a Church at <hi>Anablatha,</hi> a veile hanging in the doore of the Church, ſtained and painted, and hauing the Image as of Chriſt, or of ſome holy man; for I do not well remember whoſe Image it was: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when I ſaw the Image of a man to hang in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34256:11"/>Church of Chriſt, contrary to the authority of the Scriptures, I cut it in peeces, and gaue counſell to the Keepers of the place, rather to winde it vp, and carry out to buriall in it ſome poore man deceaſed. And a little after, I pray you command that ſuch veiles bee not hanged in the Church of Chriſt, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Religion.</p>
               <p>Here might bee ſhewed the ſtory, from what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and by what degrees this corruption entered and prevailed in the Church, till at length the ſecond councell of <hi>Nice</hi> directly againſt the word of God and all ancient practiſe of the Church, decreed the ſetting vp of Images in the Churches, and worſhipping of them</p>
               <p>For that the Doctrine of our Sauiour Chriſt and of his Apoſtles was contrary hereunto, &amp; the ſame which our Church in <hi>England</hi> doth teach and maintaine, whereof here is queſtion, hath bene already decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Therefore touching the firſt point of our religion in diuine ſeruice, which concerneth the ſubiect, which is, that God onely is to be religiouſly worſhipped, &amp; not Images, or yet any creature whatſoeuer: Thus it hath bene proued which was diſired, that our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on herein is that which the Lord Ieſus himſelfe &amp; his moſt faithfull miniſters the Apoſtles taught and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</p>
               <p>Now followeth the ſecond poynt of thoſe which are common to all diuine Seruices, that is, in what language or tongue it is to be performed: wherein the doctrine and practiſe of our Church in <hi>England</hi> is, that it be adminiſtred in a ſpeech knowne, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by all the people.</p>
               <p>In which practiſe it is now to bee ſhewed that wee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34256:12"/>haue our Religion in this reſpect, in like manner from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, teaching and ordaining ſuch adminiſtration of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Diuine Seruice is to be adminiſtred in a language which the people vnderſtand.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Sauiour Chriſt performed his owne Miniſtery in a ſpeech vnderſtood by all the people; for hee read and expounded the Scriptures to them in a tongue which they vnderſtood, as it appeareth, <hi>Luke</hi> 4. He prayed alſo in like manner, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Further alſo in ſaying, <hi>Heare yee Moyſes and the Prophets,</hi> he commandeth the reading and expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their writings to bee performed in a language that might be vnderſtood; for otherwiſe they could not heare them with any vnderſtanding, but ſhould be as deafe men; whereas his meaning there is, that they ſhould ſo heare, as they might be taught there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and forewarned to gouern the courſe of their life, as they might avoyd the torments of hell. Likewiſe hee taught his Diſciples to pray in a tongue which they vnderſtood, and in them, ſo inſtructed all other that ſhould be his Diſciples after, to call vpon God in a ſpeech knowne by them, both in the Forme he taught them ſaying, When ye pray, ſay thus: <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi> and by the direction of that prayer, to make all our petitions priuate and publike.</p>
               <p>Inſtituting alſo the Sacrament of Baptiſme, hee
<pb facs="tcp:34256:12"/>commanded his Diſciples,
<note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>To preach the Goſpell vnto all nations, and to baptize ſuch as ſhould beleeue;</hi> which teaching and beleeuing neceſſarily implyeth the vſe of a ſpeech known in the adminiſtration of Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>In like manner he inſtituted and adminiſtred the Sacrament of his Supper amongſt his Diſciples in a ſpeech which they vnderſtood, and charged them as oft as they ſhould doe the like, to preach his death vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his comming againe; wherefore it is plaine, that he intended the Sacraments ſhould not bee dumbe ſhowes and ſpectacles, but that they ſhould bee ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred as the people might know and vnderſtand the meaning of them. Finally, after his aſcenſion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other ſpiritual graces,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> he indued the Apoſtles with the guift of tongues, whereby the ſame day they ſpake to the <hi>Iewes</hi> that were then from all nations aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the great acts and mighty works of God.</p>
               <p>For it is expreſsly written, and that the people maruelled that they heard them ſpeake euery one in the language of the Countrey wherein they had been borne.</p>
               <p>By which miraculous guift, beſtowed firſt vpon the Apoſtles, then after vpon many other, and by ſuch vſe of it in teaching the people of euery nation in their owne language, it is manifeſt, that our Sauiour Chriſts ordinance is, that diuine Seruice ſhould bee adminiſtred in a ſpeach vnderſtood by all the people.</p>
               <p>This is alſo confirmed in that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his former Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> Chap. 14. ſaith, that the ordinances ſet downe by him in that place (amongſt which this was one, that no man ſhould ſpeake in the Church and Aſſembly of the people
<pb facs="tcp:34256:13"/>a ſtrange language not vnder ſtood by them, except it were interpreted) are the commandements of the Lord, that is, of Ieſus Chriſt. Thus then it appeareth to be the practiſe and ordinance of Chriſt, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Seruice ſhould be adminiſtred in a ſpeech which the people vnderſtand.</p>
               <p>Now that the Apoſtles taught the ſame is likewiſe manifeſt: for firſt, that their practiſe was ſuch, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. Where hauing receiued the guift of tongues they imployed it rightly to that end for which it was giuen, and ſpake to men of diuers tongues in the language of the Country wherein they were borne. And this was the generall practiſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as appeareth in the booke of their <hi>Acts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> debating this matter at large,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.</note> not onely teacheth manifeſtly, that all diuine Seruice ſhould bee performed in the Church in a ſpeech which the people vnderſtand, but confirmeth this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by many reaſons. In which diſcourſe it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that diuine Seruice ought to bee adminiſtred to Gods glory.
<note place="margin">verſe 47.</note> For it being the Lords co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that it ſhould be ſo performed, as the Apoſtle there calleth it, it is for the glory of God, that with all due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence it be ſo performed: Beſides this, the reaſon of this commandement doth likewiſe proue it, which is, that by ſuch meanes the knowledge of God is enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged;
<note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> the great and marueilous workes of God, as his Creation, Prouidence, &amp; redemption of the world by his onely begotten Sonne; his lawes and his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, the promiſes of the Goſpell preached in the Word, &amp; ſet out in the Sacraments, which are of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes, of life, and immortality to euery one that beleeueth, and ſuch like; are made knowne to
<pb facs="tcp:34256:13"/>men, to Gods vnſpeakeable glory, as it was by the Apoſtles. By that meanes alſo the people vnderſtand the prayers and thankſgiuing which are made by the miniſter, yeeld therin conſent to ſuch ſervices of God, and together with him, doe God that honor, that thereby they acknowledge all good guifts to come from him, and therefore that they ought to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of him by prayer, and that he is to be glorified for them with all thanksgiuing. Therefore that God may be honoured with all this honor, it behooueth and is neceſſary, that he be ſerued in the Church in a ſpeech that the people vnderſtand.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, the edification of the people doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the ſame,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.26.</note> concerning which it is the Lords ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commandement, <hi>That in the Church all things ſhould bee done to their Edification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By edification is meant their furtherance in the knowledge of God, in the vnderſtanding of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in faith, in obedience, in comfort, and all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an duties. But none of theſe can be furthered in the people, if the Miniſter vſe a language which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doth not vnderſtand. Therefore it is neceſſary for the inſtruction and comfort of the people, that the Scriptures be read and expounded, the Sacraments adminiſtred, the Prayers and thankſgiuing bee made in the Church, in a ſpeech that all the people doth vnderſtand.</p>
               <p>On the contrary part, by adminiſtring of diuine Seruice in a ſpeech not vnderſtood by the people, both God is diſhonoured, and the people are ſuffered to periſh.</p>
               <p>For touching the firſt point, Gods commandements of the right vſe of his guift: of tongues, of doing all
<pb facs="tcp:34256:14"/>things in the Church to edification, are broken, God is alſo highly diſhonoured, in that the knowledge of him is kept from the people, that his name is taken in vaine, and Seruice prophaned, and his people ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to periſh in ignorance and diſobedience. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the peoples periſhing by this meanes it is plaine, in that the blind led by the blind muſt needes periſh. By this meanes they doe remaine in their ſinnes, and namely, in the ignorance of God: which howſoeuer the adherents of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teach to bee the mother of deuotion, the word of God teacheth to be the iuſt cauſe of error, diſobedience and deſtruction.</p>
               <p>For it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Math 22.29.</note> 
                  <hi>that the ſeruant that knoweth not the will of his Maſter ſhall be beaten,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 12.47, 48.</note> it is ſaid indeed with <hi>few ſtripes</hi> in compariſon of the many ſtripes wherewith they ſhall be beaten <hi>which know their Maſters will and do it not:</hi> but by thoſe <hi>few ſtripes</hi> are meant euerlaſting torments,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.7, 8, 2.</note> as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth ſaying, <hi>And to you which are troubled, reſt with vs, when the Lord Ieſus ſhall ſhew himſelfe from heauen with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, rendering vengeance vnto them that doe not know God, and which obey not the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhall bee puniſhed with euerlaſting perdition, from the preſence of the Lord-and from the glory of his power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as the Church is edified by him that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecieth,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14, 3, 4.</note> &amp; receiueth inſtruction, exhortation, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and direction whereby they may ioyne together in Prayes and thankſgiuing: So on the contrary they want all theſe meanes when diuine Seruice is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in a ſtrange tongue which they doe not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. For the miniſter ſpeaketh not to them, that is, to their vnderſtanding; and therefore whatſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:34256:14"/>heauenly doctrine bee read or deliuered in a ſtrange tongue, the people is nothing inſtucted by it, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from the Church as ignorant of God, &amp; of all godlynes as they came to it. And as hee that is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant is not inſtructed in any thing, ſo he that is dull and ſloathfull in his duty to God or man according to Gods commandement, is not furthered by exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, nor he that is heauy in heart is not comforted;
<note place="margin">verſe 16.</note> likewiſe when the miniſter prayeth or giueth thanks, he can neither pray nor giue thanks with him, nor anſwer firly to any thing he pronounceth, becauſe he vnderſtandeth not what it is that he ſayeth.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding remaineth fruiteleſſe,</hi> and that fiue wordes ſpoken to their vnderſtanding, were more worth then many thouſands in that ſort. And in reſpect of the Prophet or miniſter hee ſaith, that in ſo doing,
<note place="margin">verſe 2, 9.</note> hee ſpeaketh (in regard of any benefit of the people) as if hee ſpake into the ayre and his ſpeech vaniſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the winde, without profit to any.</p>
               <p>Furthermore he ſayeth,
<note place="margin">verſe 7, 8, 9.</note> that the miniſter ſo ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is like one that ſhould ſound a trumpet, or ſtrike a harpe or anyother Inſtrument without diſtinction of ſounds: whereby he intendeth, that as the people not vnderſtanding could receiue by it no direction in battell, to march or retyre, or in other actions what to doe, or whereunto to prepare and diſpoſe themſelues: So in the ſeruice of God, they know not what they are directed vnto, whether to pray to God, or to giue him thankes, or to what other part of the Seruice of God they are to apply themſelues.</p>
               <p>Moreouer,
<note place="margin">verſe 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0, 23.</note> the Apoſtle affirmeth that where this diſorder hath place, they are as <hi>Barbarians</hi> one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:34256:15"/>they are as little children in vnderſtanding, yea, they will ſeeme to bee out of thir wits, and deſtitute of common ſence and reaſon.</p>
               <p>Finally, the Apoſtle addeth, that to ſpeake to the people in a language they doe not vnderſtand, is a token and ſigne of Gods wrath and anger to them. Which may be eaſily vnderſtood by ſome like thing in our life with men. For if a ſeruant or a ſonne that hath offended his Lord and Father, or a ſubiect that hath tranſgreſſed the lawes of his Prince, ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent himſelfe to him to craue pardon of his offence, and to pray to vnderſtand his pleaſure, that hee may performe it in time to come; if that Lord, that Father, or that King ſhall not graciouſly comfort his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyant, but ſpeake to him in a tongue that hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth not, and ſo diſmiſſe him, is not that a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt figne of his anger and indignation? Euen ſo when any aſſembly of Chriſtian people ſhall gather them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues together, to preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to God, to craue of him grace &amp; pardon for their ſins, to offer their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions and ſeruice to him, it muſt needes bee an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy and vncomfortable token vnto them of Gods high diſpleaſure toward them, when hee vouchſafeth not to ſpeake any gracious words vnto them that they can vnderſtand, but ſpeaketh to them in a ſtrange lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. Heereby therefore it appeareth, that to haue diuine Seruice adminiſtred in a tongue not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the people, is contrary to the doctrine of our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles; yea, and that it is childiſh, barbarous, and contrary to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſence and reaſon, vnprofitable for the people, yea a hinderance to them, and a meanes to keepe them in ignorance, and all vngodlyneſſe, and a ſigne of Gods indignation
<pb facs="tcp:34256:15"/>againſt them, and a high diſhonor to almighty God by the tranſgeſſion of his commandements, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his name in vaine. Contrariwiſe heereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that to adminiſter diuine Seruice in a tongue vnderſtood by the people, is profitable for them, and fit to further them in the knowledge, faith, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of God; and as honorable to God by making knowne his goodneſſe, mercy, Iuſtice, greatneſſe, and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fection in all reſpects vnto his Church and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. This is confirmed alſo at large by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in his former Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> Chap. 14, as it hath beened clared. Hereunto may bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that it appeareth by the 33, and 36. verſes, that the Apoſtle ordayned thus in all other Churches that were taught by him, and that the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> in that diſorder, differed both from the Church of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> and from all other Churches that at that time had receiued the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Further alſo it appeareth, that in all ages before, the true Church ſerued God with knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of that was taught them, and yeelded to God their Seruice in ſuch ſort as they knew what du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it was, which they performed vnto him. For firſt almighty God himſelfe deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered the two tables of the tenne commandements, in that ſpeach which the people vnderſtood.</p>
               <p>After alſo by his commandement often times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, both <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and the Prieſts,
<note place="margin">Exo. 19, 9. Exo. 20.18.19. Deut. 5, 10, 11 28, 29.30, &amp;c.</note> are charged to teach the people to heare and know, learne and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, the low of God. Particularly the law comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the King ſhould write the coppy of the law in a booke, coppied out of that booke which was kept by the leuitical Prieſts,
<note place="margin">Deut. 6.1, 2, 3. &amp;c.</note> wherein he is charged to reade
<pb facs="tcp:34256:16"/>all the dayes of his life,
<note place="margin">chap. 17.18, 19. Deut. 12.1.27.1. &amp;c. 29.1. &amp;c.</note> that he may learne to feare the Lord his God, and to obſerue and doe all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. In many places of the bookes of <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and eſpecially in the booke of <hi>Deut.</hi> it is ſayd, that <hi>Moyſes</hi> taught all the people the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſtatutes which the Lord had deliuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.
<note place="margin">Ioſ. 1.10, 11. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſuah</hi> in like manner dealt with all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, inſtructing and exhorting them to the obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſtatutes which God had deliuered vnto them.</p>
               <p>In the like manner did <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Chron. 16.2, 4, 7, 35, 36, 37.</note> and all the Prophets, deliuering <hi>Pſalmes</hi> and other bookes of Scriptures in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> tongue for the publique vſe of the Church of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> which they had indited in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> tongue, the common ſpeech of all the people.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe <hi>Solomon,
<note place="margin">1 Chton. 25.2, 5, &amp; 28.2, 8. &amp;c. 1 Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, 55, 57, 58, 61, 62.</note> Dauids</hi> ſon, at the dedication of the Temple which hee had builded, made his ſolemne prayers and publique ſupplications vnto God, in the hearing of all the people, in their owne <hi>Hebrew</hi> tongue which they beſt vnderſtood.</p>
               <p>And of <hi>Ioſias</hi> it is alſo particularly recorded,
<note place="margin">2 Kings 22.11 &amp; 23.2, 3. &amp;c.</note> that hee read in the hearing of all the people from the greateſt to the leaſt of them, all the words of Gods Couenant which had beene found in the houſe of the Lord.</p>
               <p>After the captiuity alſo wee reade,
<note place="margin">Ezra 8.21. &amp; 9.5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; 10.1.</note> that <hi>Ezra</hi> at a publique feaſt once or twice made his earneſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication vnto God for all the people, they hearing and ſo vnderſtanding him, that men, women, and children, wept and lamented exceedingly.</p>
               <p>And in the booke of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> it is written, <hi>Ezra</hi> did reade the booke of the law of God from mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to mid-day before all the people, men, women,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34256:16"/>and all, that for vnderſtanding were fit to heare, and that all the people was attentiue to the booke of the law, and when <hi>Ezra</hi> bleſſed, all the people ſaid <hi>Amen,
<note place="margin">Nehe. 8.2, 3, 4, 7, 8, 9, 10, &amp;c.</note> Amen,</hi> with lifting vp their hands, and bowing downe their heads, they worſhipped God with their faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ground.</p>
               <p>In the time of our Sauiour Chriſt, the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth, <hi>Moyſes was read and preached euery Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath in the Synagogues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 15.21. &amp; 13.15.</note> of which cuſtome wee reade an example in the 13 of the <hi>Asts,</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>that after the reading of the law and the Prophets, Paul and Barnabas were willed to exhort the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the example of our Sauiour Chriſt, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly written, as hath beene touched before,
<note place="margin">Luke 4.16, 17, 21, 22.</note> that hee entred into the Synagogue of <hi>Nazareth</hi> vpon the ſabbath day as his manner was, and there ſtanding vp to reade, when the booke of the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> had beene deliuered to him, hee opened it and read that which is written in the begining of the 61 Chap. of that Prophecy. And further that hauing deliuered againe the booke, hee ſate downe, and the eyes of all that were in the Synogogue were bent vpon him. To whom hauing ſayd, that that Scripture was fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that day in their hearing, they all bare him witneſſe that it was ſo, and maruelled at the ſpeeches full of grace that proceeded out of his mouth.</p>
               <p>The like practiſe of the Apoſtles in their Liturgie and publique miniſtry in the Church at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the booke of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and namely, in theſe places <hi>Acts</hi> 2, 4, 7, 8, 14, 22, 37, 38, 40, 41, 42, 46, 47. Throughout the ſame booke, and likewiſe in all Epiſtles of the Apoſtles it is playne, that this was their practiſe amongſt the diſperſed <hi>Iewes</hi> and the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34256:17"/>Churches of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as of the <hi>Romanes, Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and the reſt; yea that they did ſo ordaine in all Churches in their time, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33, 36, 37.</p>
               <p>For the time ſucceeding, it appeareth by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logeticall writings of <hi>Iuſtin Martyr, Tertullian,</hi> and others, that the Liturgies in their time, were ſuch as the people vnderſtood. The like appeareth in <hi>Ierome,</hi> who was ſo deſirous to further the knowledge of Religion in the common ſort, as hee tranſlated the Scriptures, into the <hi>Dalmaticall,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sclauonian</hi> tongue, for the vſe of his Country men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origens</hi> Hexapla and Octopla bookes, ſetting out the Scripture in ſo many diuers tranſlations, witneſſe the like care and deſite in him. And of others, <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> writeth, that the Latine tranſlations were not to be num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red The Liturgies that go vnder the name of <hi>Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> declare alſo, that in the time wherein they were written, when ſoeuer it was (for they cannot be of their time, but latter) the Church vnderſtood the Scripture, Prayer, Thankeſgiuing, and other parts of diuine Seruice that was adminiſtred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. And in the Eaſt Church it continued ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>long time, as app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>areth by many exhortations of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and other of the <hi>Greeke</hi> Teachers, to the reading of the Scriptures, and by ſome parts of the Liturgie, whereof mention is made in their writings. So did it like wiſe long continue in the Weſt Church, euen till almoſt all things were corrupted, and that darkeneſſe had ouer caſt the face of the heauens, and taken the light thereof from theſe parts of the earth; namely, in the Church of <hi>Rome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> which howſoeuer it hath preuailed and continued a long time in diuers parts, and eſpecially in theſe of the Weſt; yet in this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34256:17"/>bleſſed age of reformation, it hath pleaſed God to driue away that darkeneſſe, and to cauſe the light of his countenance ſo comfortably to ſhine vnto vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as that now in our owne tongue Gods holy word is read and expounded vnto vs, the Sacraments adminiſtred, Prayers, and thankſgiuinges are offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp vnto God, and the whole Seruice of God in <hi>England</hi> is performed in a ſpeech which all our <hi>Engliſh</hi> people vnderſtand. In which reſpect it hath beene proued, that our Religion in <hi>England,</hi> is that which was taught by our Sauiour Chriſt and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtles. And thus much may ſuffiſe alſo for this poynt, being the ſecond generall here conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in all Diuine Seruice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Of the reading and expounding to the people the word of God, and not the Legends and fables of men.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>ow it followeth to proceed to declare the like in the ſundry parts of Gods Seruice. The chiefe parts of diuine Seruice (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles teach, ſpeaking of their miniſtry to whom firſt the diſpenſation of Chriſtian Religion, and of the myſteries of God, and the whole adminiſtration of Gods Seruice then was committed) conſiſteth in the Word of God, whereunto belong the Sacraments as viſible words, ſetting out the ſame doctrine of the Goſpel; and in Prayer whereunto alſo thankſigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is to be referred. For thus are performed what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Miniſters are to declare vnto the Church in Gods behalfe, and what duty and feruice the Church offereth vnto God on the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part. Wherefore all Diuine Seruice conſiſting in theſe two principall
<pb facs="tcp:34256:18"/>partes; and the former hereof being the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the word, and that firſt in the reading and expounding of the Scriptures: the next thing to bee ſhewed is, that our Religion and ſeruice of God in <hi>England,</hi> in that concerneth the reading and expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the word of God and no Legends or fables, is ſuch as was taught by Ieſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>For clearing whereof, it is firſt to be vnderſtood, that in <hi>England</hi> it is appointed that the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the writings of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> the Prophets, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, be read vnto the people, and not any Legends of Saints (as they are called) or other like vncertaine or fabulous writings, as haue beene vſed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to bee read in the churches ſubiect to the Sea of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now thus to ſerue God, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, haue taught, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by their doctrine and practiſe.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith by <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 16.29, 31.</note> They haue <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the Prophets, heare they them. And againe, If they heare not <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the Prophets, they would not bee perſwaded, no although one ſhould riſe from the dead.
<note place="margin">Iohn 5.39. Math. 22.29. Math. 12.3.7. &amp; 21.16, 41.</note> Againe, hee ſayth, <hi>Search ye the Scriptures,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ye are deceiued becauſe ye know not the Seriptures.</hi> And how often doth he ſay, <hi>Haue ye not heard, how reade you?</hi> and with many like ſpeeches referring them to the Doctrine of the Scriptures, declareth the ordinance of God, the duty of the people, and the practiſe of the Church at that time, to haue beene ſuch, as that in the publique aſſemblies that which was read and taught the people was the word of God,
<note place="margin">Luke 4.16, 31</note> and not any fables of the Iewes.</p>
               <p>Further alſo the practiſe of our Sauiour was agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thereunto, for it is noted to haue beene his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:34256:18"/>and cuſtome, vpon the Sabbath dayes, wherein <hi>Moyſes</hi> was read and expounded vnto the Church, to enter into the Synagogues and to teach the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>Now this cuſtome of his in one place, is ſo parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly reported, as that it is ſaid that hee came to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth</hi> where hee had beene brought vp, and entered according as he had beene wont into the Synagogue vpon the Sabbath day, and ſtood vp to reade; then there was deliuered vnto him the booke of <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet, which he hauing vnfolded &amp; opened, found the place where it was written, <hi>The Spirit of God, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 17.</note> Which text after hee had read, hee expounded vnto them, and out of it preached the Goſpell of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God vnto them.</p>
               <p>And it is further added, that the people heard him and the eyes of all that were in the Synagogue were faſtned vpon him:
<note place="margin">verſe 20.</note> By which place it is manifeſt that our Sauiour Chriſt by this example and cuſtome of his, did reade and expound the word of God, the writings of the holy Scriptures giuen by diuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, which are the bookes that ought to be read and expounded and preached vpon in all Chriſtian Churches, and not vaine diſcourſes ſuch as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth old wiues tales.</p>
               <p>This alſo was the doctrine and vſe of the Apoſtles: For being followers of Chriſt, all their Doctrine was out of the Scriptures, as it appeareth by that is ſayd <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42. That the Church continued in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>And in the ſame Chap. the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to haue taught the Doctrine of the reſurrection of Chriſt, out of the <hi>Pſalmes:</hi> Likewiſe the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb facs="tcp:34256:19"/>writing to the diſperſed <hi>Iewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19.</note> doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them for attending to the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.
<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.20.</note> Likewiſe by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> it is written, <hi>that the Church is builded vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Ieſus Chriſt being the low corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone;</hi> which is ſpoken, in reſpect of their Doctrine preached by them, in their time, and after for the ſubſtance of it ſet downe in writing by the will of God, for the vſe of the Church for euer.</p>
               <p>This appeareth alſo, in that the Scripture giuen by the inſpitation of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> is ſayd, to bee that which is written,
<note place="margin">2, Tim. 3.16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>to teach vs, to comfort, to reforme, to rebuke, and to inſtruct in all righteouſneſſe, to make a man wiſe to Saluation by faith in Chriſt, and to make the man of God perfect, fully furniſhed for any good worke.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to the auncient ordinance of God, <hi>Moyſes</hi> (that is,
<note place="margin">Act. 15.21.</note> the Law and bookes written by <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>) were vſed to bee read (as the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth) euery Sabbath day in the Synagogues. The writings of the Prophets alſo were ſo read amongſt them, as it appeareth by that is written <hi>Acts</hi> 13. that after the reading of the Law, and of the Prophets, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> preached in the Synagogue at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioche.</hi> And of the ſame Apoſtle it is ſayd, that he confirmed Ieſus to bee Chriſt; that is, the <hi>Meſſias</hi> promiſed of God,
<note place="margin">Act. 26.12.</note> by proofes taken out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and as hee teſtifieth of him ſelfe, hee taught nothing beſides that, which had bin taught before in the Law, and in the Prophets.</p>
               <p>Thus by all theſe enidences it is manifeſt, that our Religion in <hi>England,</hi> concerning this part of the Seruice of God, is the ſame which was taught by our Sauiour Chriſt, and by his Apoſtles, <hi>viz.</hi> in that
<pb facs="tcp:34256:19"/>the holy Scriptures are publiquely read vnto the people, and alſo the people is taught Chriſtian Religion by the expounding and preaching of the ſame vnto them; and that no fooliſh fables, nor old wiues tales, are read vnto them, as they are read vnto the people vnder the Popes gouernement, which ought not to bee.</p>
               <p>Of this ſort are the Legends of Saints, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Legenda aurea,</hi> that is, the golden Legend, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a report of the Liues and miracles of Saints. But howſoeuer they haue named it a golden booke, yet ſome of their owne writers of beſt iudgement, (as <hi>Ludouicus Vines</hi>) cenſure it for a booke written by a man of a leaden heart, (which is for the baſeneſſe of the reports, that are without wit or reaſon) and of a braſen forehead, which is for the ſhameleſſe and impudent boldneſſe, reporting things ſo fabulous and incredible; It needeth not to proue this by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry particulars.</p>
               <p>This is playne, by ſtrange deuiſes and reports, concerning perſons that neuer were, for any thing that appeareth by any ſtory of credit, as of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>George,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Catherine</hi> and ſuch like fictions, deuices for inſtructions of life, as <hi>Eſops</hi> Fables were for morals. It is likewiſe manifeſt in many other of ſuch as haue beene, and are mentioned by Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ographers, but the reports there made of them, are ſo incredible, ſo fabulous, ſo homely, and ſo ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, as they are not tollerable to bee read in any moſt baſe company, much leſſe in the Ecleſiaſticall aſſemblies, of a people profeſſing to come together to learne to know the will of God, and to offer vnto him their ſeruice and prayers.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:34256:20"/>
               <p> Now that ſuch things ought not to bee read in the Church, is manifeſt, becauſe the Lord forbiddeth to adde to his word,
<note place="margin">Deut. 4.2.</note> and hee hath giuen no comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of hearing any but his owne Sonne, of whom it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Math. 17.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Heare yee him.</hi> The Scriptures of Diuine inſpiration, are the onely light that God hath giuen vs to bee directed by, in things concerning his Seruice;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> For of them onely it is ſayd, <hi>That they are a Lanterne vnto our feet, and a light vnto our ſteps.</hi> That <hi>they are written for our learning, Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>That by patience and conſolation of the Scripture, wee might haue hope.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15.</note> Likewiſe, wee are taught, <hi>That the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are able to make a man wiſe to ſaluation by faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> and finally, that they are of vſe, <hi>for doctrine, reproofe, reformation, and inſtruction in righteouſneſſe,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16, 17. 1 Tim. 1.4. &amp; 4.7. 2 Tim. 4.3 4. Tit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.14.</note> that the man of God may bee made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and fully accompliſhed for euery good worke and duty.</hi> But on the contrary part, there is expreſſe Charge giuen, not to attend to fables, which are alſo called prophane fables, <hi>Iewiſh</hi> fables, and old wiues tales, whereof the Apoſtle giueth ſo much greater charge becauſe hee did foreſee and propheſie, that ſuch times would come in the Church, that men would turne away their eares from hearing ſound Doctrine, and would turne them to the hearing of tales and fables. And as this part of the myſtery of iniquities was then foreſhewed, ſo after it mightily preuailed, and yet doth in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but not of many ages after the Apoſtles time. For <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> reporting to the Emperour <hi>Antonirus,</hi> the order of diuine Seruice vſed by the Churches of Chriſt in his time, ſayth, that they read the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and after had exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb facs="tcp:34256:20"/>made vnto them, grounded vpon the ſame. Likewiſe <hi>Tertullian</hi> declareth after his report of the Prayers of the Church,
<note place="margin">Lib. apologet.</note> that they met together alſo to heare the reading of the Scriptures, for ſaith hee, <hi>with ſuch holy voyces</hi> (meaning the Scriptures) <hi>wee feede our faith, raiſe our hope, faſten our confidence, and ſtrengthen good order by often mention of the precepts.</hi> and further faith, <hi>that they had alſo exhortation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes, and exerciſe of diuine Cenſures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After when by proceſſe of time ſuch corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as that other writings beſides the holy Scriptures began to bee read in the Church,
<note place="margin">2. Coun. of Carthage, ca. 47.</note> a Councell held at <hi>Carthage</hi> for the reforming of ſuch diſorder; ordained <hi>That nothing beſides the holy Scriptures ſhould bee read in the Churches vnder the name of the holy bookes.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the myſtery of iniquity ſo preuailed with time, that in the Churches ſubiect to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> vnder pretence of the liues and miracles of Saints, moſt ſottiſh and fooliſh fables and tales were publiquely read in the Church vnto the people, wherein it cannot bee vttered, what wrong was done to God, and to his Church. <hi>What hath chaffe to doe with wheate?</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Ieremy,</hi> Chap.
<note place="margin">Ier. 23.28.</note> 23. verſe 28. For the Lord hath ordayned, that his people ſhould bee fedd with his holy word as with the fineſt wheate, yea, as with <hi>Manna,</hi> the bread of heauen, and they withholding it from the people of God, and keeping it ſhut vp vnder a ſtrange lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, feede the people with ſuch fables and follies as with chaffe, yea, as with draffe more fit for ſwine.</p>
               <p>The word of God is alſo a fountaine of liuing water, at which the people of God may be refreſhed with comfort, but they filled vp thoſe Springes of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34256:21"/>life,
<note place="margin">Ier. 2.13</note> and ſent them to drinke at pits of their owne diggings which could hold no water, and as it were to the filthy channels of the ſtreets, to fetch their drinke there. <hi>Should not a people aske counſel of their God? ſhould they goe for counſell from the liuing to the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſult they with the Law and the testimony</hi> (ſayth the Prophet <hi>Eſay) they which aduiſe otherwiſe,
<note place="margin">Eſay, 8.19, 20</note> is there any ſparke of light in any of them?</hi> Now to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with the Scripture which is giuen by Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, is to conſult with God, neither is there now any other ordinary meanes to conſult with God but by his holy word. Therefore all other meanes to conſult are forbidden and reputed, as if a man that vſed them did aske counſell (as <hi>Saul</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) of the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I came vnto you,</hi> ſayth our Sauiour, <hi>in my Fathers name, and you did not receiue mee,</hi> but if one come to you in his owne name,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.43.</note> you will receiue him: And thus it is with thoſe that receiue not the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that are the word of Chriſt, except it bee in an vnknowne tongue; but reade fables and tales to the people, in a ſpeech which they all vnderſtand. It is a maruaile that the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> is not aſhamed of this enormity vnto this day, but that in ſtead of Gods holy word, that conuerteth and comforteth the ſoule, they reade to the people ſuch ridiculous follies as peruert and deſtroy the ſoule: But howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they doe thus highly diſhonour God herein, it is manifeſt, by that which hath bin ſaid, that our Religion in <hi>England,</hi> in this poynt alſo of reading Gods word, and not ridiculous tales to the Church of God, is the ſame which was taught by our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:34256:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of Preaching.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>England</hi> as wee haue the word of God publiquely read in the Church, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tales and follies; ſo hath it beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the endeauour of our Church, that the ſame word of God might bee alſo expounded vnto the people, that ſo they might bee taught to know the Articles of true Chriſtian Religion, with the grounds thereof deliuered in the holy Scriptures, and haue it applied to their inſtruction in godlineſſe, to the reproofe of the diſobedient, to the comfort of the comfortleſſe, and to euery good vſe for which God hath ordained it. To this end, at the ordination of Miniſters, they are earneſtly exhorted to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this duty, and there are many bountifull allowances in diuers parts of the Realme aſſigned for Preachers to attend vpon that Seruice.</p>
               <p>In performance whereof there are alſo required two things. The one is that the Doctrine be ſound,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.8. 2 Tim. 3, 4. 2 Tim. 4.12.</note> that is, holy, and grounded vpon the Scriptures; The other, that this duty bee performed with all faithfulneſſe and diligence. Now in all theſe points alſo, our Religion is the ſame which was taught by our Sauiour Chriſt and by his Apoſtles. For our Sauiour leauing his commiſſion with his Apoſtles for publiſhing of his Goſpell, ſaid,
<note place="margin">Math. 28.19.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Teach yee all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and <hi>Teach them to obſcrue whatſoeuer I haue giuen you in charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe before that time, he had ſaid vnto them,
<pb facs="tcp:34256:22"/>who is a faithfull and prudent ſteward, whom the Lord ſhall ſet ouer his houshold that hee may giue them their portion in due ſeaſon:
<note place="margin">Lnke. 12.42.43, 44.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed ſhall that ſeruant bee whom the Lord at his comming ſhall finde ſo doing,</hi> I tell you truely hee will let him ouer all his goods.</p>
               <p>This appeareth alſo in the earneſt charge thrice giuen and repeated at one time to <hi>Peter,</hi> that as hee loued the Lord,
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 21.15, 16.17. Tit. 2.8. Tit. 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>hee ſhould feede his ſheepe.</hi> Likewiſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth <hi>Titus</hi> to preach the wholeſome word that cannot bee condemned, and to ſee that there bee integrity and incorruption in his Doctrine.</p>
               <p>And writing to <hi>Timothy</hi> he exhorteth him with a moſt earneſt conteſtation before God,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1, 2.</note> and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that is to iudge both the quicke and the dead at his illuſtrous comming, and in his kingdome, that hee preach the word, bee inſtant ſeaſonably and vnſeaſonably, and ſo forth. So the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> with a like conteſtation exhorteth the Elders of the diſperſed <hi>Iewes</hi> to feede the flocke of God that was with them,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.1, 2.4.</note> willingly and with a ready and cheerefull minde, and promiſing them ſo doing to receiue at the appearing of the Arch-Paſtor a Garland that ſhall not wither, or of Flower-gentle whoſe beauty and colour doth not fade nor wither away. Thus it is proued that our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles haue taught, that the word of God ſhould bee prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the people, and that the Doctrine deliuered out of it, ſhould bee ſound, holy, and warranted by the Scripture, and that the ſame ought to bee prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with all faithfull care, and diligence. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what godly care and endeauor is amongſt vs
<pb facs="tcp:34256:22"/>in theſe reſpects, is according to the Doctrine taught by Chriſt himſelfe and his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>And of ſuch care, many Iniunctions, Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Canons, Statutes, and Acts of Parlament, made both for the aduancement of preaching of Gods word, and alſo for the faithfull diligence of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters therein, doe plentifully teſtifie. But eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe are moſt worthy honor, which prouide for the ſincerity and ſoundneſſe of the Doctrine of faith, and of the Sacraments, ſet downe in the booke of Articles, agreed vpon in the Conuocation, in the yeere of our Lord 1562. and in the 13 yeere of the reigne of our late gracious Queene, ordained to bee acknowledged ſound and holy, as it is by ſuch as ſhall take ordinary care and charge of ſoules within the Church of <hi>England.</hi> All which Articles haue beene often Iuſtified by many learned Treatiſes ioyntly and ſeuerally concerning them. For which cauſe it ſeemeth not needfull vpon occaſion to enter into the debating and prouing of them (which would aske a long time) eſpecially of the errors of the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> which are very many, &amp; were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to bee confuted.</p>
               <p>But if particular queſtions be moued of any one of them, no neceſſary duty ſhall bee wanting, to proue the truth and ſoundneſſe of that may bee doubted of, and to diſproue any error that may bee main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained againſt it. For this time, &amp; the poynt that is in hand, it may ſuffice heere to haue mentioned the care of our Church in <hi>England,</hi> that the word of God bee not onely read, but alſo expounded vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that by warrant of the ſame, they may bee taught the truth of Chriſtian Religion, and that
<pb facs="tcp:34256:23"/>with all faithfullneſſe and diligence, and that herein our Religion is the ſame which Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles taught and deliuered vnto vs.</p>
               <p>On the contrary part, exceeding great is the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this behalfe. Firſt, in that there haue beene of many ages ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny errours as haue beene diſcouered in their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, &amp; yet they haue confirmed the ſame by their laſt Councell holden at <hi>Trent,</hi> and doe ſtill main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame, both by their continuall writings, and alſo at ſuch times as they pretend to preach the Goſpell of Chriſt vnto the people; Further alſo, how violently ſoeuer they contend that all their Doctrine is true, yet haue they little care to inſtruct the people in it. This appeareth, in that it is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which they teach and hold, that ignorance is the mother of deuotion. Likewiſe, in that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reade the word of God publiquely to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in a knowne Language, nor ſuffer them priuately ſo to reade it. This appeareth alſo by that their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Prieſts are generally ſo ignorant, as hardly one Preacher can bee found amongſt them in a great Country. Finally their diſpenſations for non reſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and for multiplying of benefices, and for atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance vpon other perſons, and matters, are ſo ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, that it manifeſtly declareth, as experience alſo hath taught, &amp; yet doth in moſt places, that it is one of the leaſt cares that they haue by Preaching to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the people.</p>
               <p>Whereby it is plaine, that heerein they are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the doctrine &amp; practiſe, inſtitution &amp; ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles.
<note place="margin">Luk 21.37, 38. and 4.16.</note> For of their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all attendance vpon this duty, their earneſt charges
<pb facs="tcp:34256:23"/>to all Miniſters of the Goſpell,
<note place="margin">Act. 10.18.19, 20.21.26, 27, 28, 29.30, 31.32. 1, Pet. 5.2.3, 4. 2, Tim. 4.1.2. Ioh. 21.15, 16.17.</note> there are manifeſt teſtimonies in the Scriptures, from whoſe examples and commandements they ſwaruing ſo farre, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that they little remember or regard the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt obteſtation of the Apoſtle made before God and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and with mention of his glorious Kingdome with comming to iudge the quick and the dead. They little regard the great charge giuen by our Sauiour Chriſt to the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> that as he loued him he ſhould feed his ſheepe. Finally they ſmally regard either the promiſe of the Garland that neuer withereth, or the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the puniſhment of the vnfaithful ſeruant, that is to bee cut in two, and to receiue his portion with Hypocrits and Infidels. Thus as theſe enormities are iuſtly reprooued, ſo our contrary proceedings in <hi>England</hi> are iuſtified in the care that is held, that the doctrine preached ſhould bee holy and true, and that the preachers ſhould faithfully and diligently inſtruct the people in the ſame. And thus much of the word of God both read and preached in our Churches in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Sacraments.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T followeth to conſider of the Sacraments and of prayer. Concerning the Sacraments, our Church in <hi>England</hi> doth profeſſe, that they are in nature holy ſignes and ſeales of the doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of the Goſpell, and of the righteouſneſſe that is
<pb facs="tcp:34256:24"/>by faith thereof. In number alſo wee profeſſe that there are two: <hi>viz.</hi> Baptiſme and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And that our Religion herein is that which Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught, is thus proued. That Ieſus Chriſt ordayned theſe two Sacraments, is moſt manifeſt in the Goſpell, wherein is declared, both that Chriſt ordained theſe two, and in what manner hee appoynted them to bee adminiſtred. We reade alſo in the Goſpell,
<note place="margin">Math 28.19, 20. &amp; 26.26</note> and in other bookes of the new Teſtament, that the Apoſtles accordingly did admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter them both.</p>
               <p>But of any other Sacrament wee reade not, that either our Sauiour Chriſt miniſtred and ordained any, nor that the Apoſtles did adminiſter any other. As for thoſe fiue which the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> addeth to the number of the Sacraments, ſome of them wee acknowledge to bee holy ordinances, and ſtates of life, allowed in the Scripture, but haue not like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with Baptiſme and the Lords Supper; and ſome haue beene brought into the Church vpon a corrupt following of examples not intended for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this queſtion is at large debated in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to another queſtion concerning this matter, it may ſuffice to haue ſaid thus much in generall touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sacraments.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Sacraments as farre as we differ from the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> and haue reformed the abuſes thereof in the adminiſtration of them, wee admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter them in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſpeech, with declaration of the chiefe doctrines ſigned by them, wherein our Religion and practiſe is according to the word of God. For it hath beene Gods good pleaſure alwayes,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34256:24"/>that the Sacraments ſhould not be as dumbe ſhewes and ſpectacles, but ſo adminiſtred as the people might bee taught to vnderſtand what were the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines that were ſigned and confirmed by them.</p>
               <p>This was alſo the Doctrine of our Sauiour Chriſt, as appeareth by this that giuing charge to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles heereof, he ſaith, <hi>Teach all Nations,
<note place="margin">Math. 28.19.</note> baptiſing them,</hi> declaring thereby that the meaning and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for confirmation whereof hee ordained Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, ſhould bee declared. And of the Sacrament of his Supper, ſaith, <hi>As oft as yee doe this,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.26.</note> ſhew forth the Lords death till he come.</hi> And againe, <hi>Doe yee this in remembrance of me.</hi> Now Chriſt taught the Doctrine of that ordinance which hee there inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and deliuered. Such was alſo the Doctrine of the Apoſtles in all places of the New Teſtament, that make mention of their Doctrine and adminiſtration of the Sacraments of Baptiſme,
<note place="margin">Act. 2.38.41 &amp; 10.47, 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Act, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.7.</note> and of the Lords Supper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Baptiſme.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Articularly concerning Baptiſme, wee adminiſter it without adding thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to exorciſme, or adiuring the diuell to goe out of the child. Becauſe it is not written that our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles vſed any ſuch ceremony, or appointed any ſuch to be vſed in the adminiſtration of it. Further alſo becauſe it is a ſuperſtitious ceremony in ſundry reſpects and grounded vpon a falſe ſuppoſition, that the infants that are to bee baptized are poſſeſſed with the diuell.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34256:25"/>For our Sauiour ſaith that <hi>Theirs is the kingdome of heauen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 19.14. 1 Cor. 7.14.</note> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that <hi>The children of Chriſtian Parents are holy:</hi> yea though but one of their Parents be a Chriſtian and faithfull.</p>
               <p>And wee adminiſter Baptizme without exorciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me or adiuration; ſo doe wee likewiſe without ſalt, ſpittle, creame, honny, oyle, Chriſme, Candlelight &amp;c. Which Ceremonies wee doe not vſe in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Baptizme. 1. Becauſe there is neither commandement nor example of the vſe of any of them giuen in the Scriptures by our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles. 2. Becauſe wee haue ſufficient commandement in the Scriptures for the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it, that is, without any of theſe. 3. Becauſe wee haue many examples in the Scripture of ſuch as were lawfully and duly baptized without the vſe of any of theſe.
<note place="margin">Act. 2.41. and 10, 48. &amp; 16 33.</note> 4. Theſe are the deuices of men, added to the ordinances of Chriſt, and to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, according to which inuentions it is not lawfull to ſerue God. Thus it appeareth that our Religion in this part alſo is according to the Doctrine and practice of our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T followeth now to ſpeake of the Lords Supper, which is the other Sacrament of the new Teſtament. In the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which Sacrament, the order vſed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is, after due preparation
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34256:25"/>by euery ones tryall of themſelues in faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to adminiſter it with declaration of the inſtitution of Chriſt, and of the doctrine ſigned and confirmed by it in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tongue, that all the people may vnderſtand.</p>
               <p>We doe alſo adminiſter it in both kinds, of bread and wine. Further the miniſter doth take the bread and giue thanks, breake it and deliuer it to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants. Likewiſe hee taketh the cup and after thanks-giuing, powreth out the wine in the cup to bee deliuered to all that are to bee partakers of the communion. The people that doe communicate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bread and eate it, and the wine likewiſe, and drinke it.</p>
               <p>Now the end and vſe of all this is added hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, which is in generall the ſolemne commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the death of Chriſt. In particular, and that firſt in regard of God, and of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, to magnifie the goodneſſe of God, in not ſparing to giue his onely begotten Sonne for the redemption of the world; and to giue him moſt due thankes for ſuch his vnſpeakable grace and mercy. It is likewiſe to glorifie our Sauiour Chriſt, and to giue thankes for his exceeding loue to mankind, in that for our redemption, he hath vouchſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fed to humble himſelfe to take vpon him our nature and the forme of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and in that nature to humble himſelfe for vs euen to the death, and that the accurſſed death of the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>In reſpect of men <hi>viz,</hi> both of all other to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our Chriſtian faith; and alſo in regard of our ſelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, that our faith and by i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Communion with Chriſt may be increaſed, whereby wee may bee
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34256:26"/>made more and more partakers of him, and of all his benefits, both of grace in this life, namely of the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, of ſanctification, of gifts needfull for our particular calling, and in the world to come of euerlaſting life and glory. Finally, that theſe things being thus performed with thankſgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and petitions for our ſelues, and the whole mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant Church of Chriſt, agreeably to Gods word, and that ſacred action, the whole adminiſtration is finiſhed to the glory of God, and the edification of ſuch as haue beene partakers of that holy table.</p>
               <p>In all which adminiſtration there is nothing but that was taught and done by our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles.
<note place="margin">Math. 26.26, &amp;c. Mark. 14.22, &amp;c. Luk. 22.4, 19, &amp;c. 1, Cor. 11, 22.23, &amp;c.</note> For our Sauiour at the firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of his holy Supper, deliuered the Doctrine which hee intended ſhould be confirmed by it, and that in a ſpeech vnderſtood by his Diſciples, and gaue commandement vnto them to doe the like, and to ſhew forth by it, the comemmoration of his death vntill his coming againe. In like manner did the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.
<note place="margin">Act. 2.42.</note> For the Euangeliſt <hi>Luke</hi> reporting that the Diſciples continued in the doctrine of the Apoſtles in communication, in breaking of bread, and in prayers; declareth that the Apoſtles ioyned Doctrine with the adminiſtration of this Sacrament, and with prayer, &amp; all the actions of that ſpirituall communion and ſocietie, which the Church of Chriſt at <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> had together. The like appeareth in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1, Cor. 11.23.</note> both in that hee profeſſeth to haue deliuered to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> concerning this Sacrament, that which hee had receiued of the Lord, and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly by that long ſpeech which hee had at <hi>Troas,</hi> before the adminiſtration of this Sacrament,
<note place="margin">Act. 20, 7. Act. 2, 42.</note> there
<pb facs="tcp:34256:26"/>alſo noted and comprehended vnder breaking of bread. Moreouer concerning the adminiſtration in both kinds, it is moſt manifeſt by the ſtory of the Goſpel, and by the writing of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> that leſus Chriſt tooke bread, and brake it, and gaue it to his Diſciples; and likewiſe that he tooke wine, and hauing giuen thanks, not only gaue it to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to drinke, but with theſe expreſſe words, <hi>Drinke yee all of this.</hi> Whereby it is moſt plaine that our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Lords Supper, in both kinds, is according to that the Lord himſelfe did at the firſt inſtitution of it. Yea it is alſo according to that hee commanded after to bee done, in that he ſaid, <hi>Doe yee this in remembrance of mee;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26.27.</note> And more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly concerning the cup; <hi>Drinke yee all of this.</hi> Which being the Doctrine, practice, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Lord himſelfe, it cannot be doubted but the Apoſtles did both ſo adminiſter it, and teach concerning the adminiſtration of it; eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth (which faithfulneſſe is to be eſteemed to haue bene alſo in all the other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles) that hee deliuered to the Church that which hee receiued from the Lord. <hi>viz.</hi> as before hath bene declared, that the Lord deliuered to his Diſciples both bread and wine. Whereby it is to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that whereas ſometimes this Sacrament is noted or comprehended vnder the ſpeech of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king bread, that it is not meant, that it was admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in bread only, but it is a ſpeech that by one part doth note the whole Supper of the Lord adminiſtred in both kindes of bread and wine; which is confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo to haue bene ſo deliuered by the Apoſtles, by the practice of the primitiue church, which did ſo
<pb facs="tcp:34256:27"/>adminiſter it, as it appeareth by the Apologie of <hi>Iuſtine Martyr,</hi> ſo reporting of the adminiſtration of it. Now as this order of adminiſtration of the Lords Supper vſed in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> church thus appeareth to haue beene receiued from the Doctrine, practiſe and commandement of Chriſt him ſelfe and of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and ſo to haue beene vſed in the Primitiue Church; ſo on the Contrary part, the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> hath in effect aboliſhed the Supper of the Lord in their Maſſe, hauing neither bread nor wine in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of it.</p>
               <p>For the bread they ſay, after Conſecration is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the <hi>reall</hi> body of Chriſt, which being fleſh and bones, it followeth by their Doctrine, that there is no bread left in the Sacrament as it is miniſtred by them: which errours of the <hi>reall,</hi> and bodily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and of the change and tranſubſtantiation of the bread into the fleſh of Chriſt, are conuicted to be moſt abſurd and erroneous both by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and by common ſence and reaſon. For the Scripture (euen after the conſecration and ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part of the bread to that ſacred and holy vſe, to bee a Sacrament of the Lords Body) doth often call it bread, as it appeareth in the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> Chap. 11. where it is ſaid, <hi>The Bread that wee breake is it not the Cemmanion of the body of Chriſt?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pillip. 2.6.7. Heb. 4.15.</note> And in the Chap. 11. <hi>As oft as yee ſhall eate of this bread,</hi> and after diuers times. This appeareth alſo in that the Scriptures teach that Chriſt became Man, hauing the true nature of man like to vs in all things ſinne only excepted. Which prooueth that his body cannot bee in the ſmall compaſſe of a wafer cake, hauing the dimenſions and meaſures of length,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34256:27"/>breadth and thickneſſe, which other mens bodyes haue. And whereas it is pretended to bee ſo by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, this is diſproued two waies. Firſt, in that the Scriptures which make expreſſe mention of Chriſts miracles, doe neuer make mention nor obſeruation of any miracle to haue bene done by him, in this changing bread into his body. Secondly the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures making mention of any miraculous change of one ſubſtance into another, doe declare that the change hath beene ſuch as was to bee iudged, diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and perceiued by all meanes of vnderſtanding both of ſence and reaſon. As for example, when Chriſt changed water into wine,
<note place="margin">Iohn, 2.9: 10: 11.</note> the wine was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued to be wine by the ſight and taſt ſo diſcerning of it. But in this caſe neither doth the eye ſee any fleſh, nor the taſt diſcerne of any, but contrariwiſe that the bread remaineth bread ſtill in ſubſtance ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the fight, ſmelling, ſauour, and the taſte thereof; by the effect of nouriſhing, by the place where it is on earth, and by the accidents of white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſmalneſſe, roundneſſe, and by that it becometh in time to bee ſubiect to bee mouldy, and that it may bee eaten by Mice, and Vermine.</p>
               <p>But it is moſt falſe, erronious, and blaſphemous, to affirme that the body of Chriſt which is moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in heauen, can bee ſubiect to any of theſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. Beſides, how great is that blaſphemy whereby it is ſaid vnder pretence of this tranſubſtantiation, that the Prieſt is the Creator of his Creator, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of his maker; But it would aske a long time to lay out the arguments &amp; reaſons that confute this abſurd &amp; damnable error, and this labour is already partly beſtowed in anſwer to another queſtion of this
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34256:28"/>kinde. Therefore thus much may heere ſuffice to ſhew, that by the errour of tranſubſtantiation, there is not left any bread vpon the Lords table, by them that affirme the bread to bee changed into floſh, and therefore that this part of the Sacrament is wanting in the Maſſe. Now for the other, the ſame may bee ſaid concerning the wine, which they doe likewiſe teach to bee turned into the very blood of Chriſt. But it appeareth alſo further, in that they haue ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiouſly robbed the Lords table of that bleſſed cup that belongeth to it. For although they ſuffer the Prieſt to drinke of the cuppe, and the people alſo to drinke wine, yet the wine that they giue the people is not conſecrated nor any part of the Sacrament. Therefore in ſuch adminiſtration is committed a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious abuſe, in robbing the Lords table and his people of the cuppe of bleſſing, which is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh) of the blood of Chriſt: and contrariwiſe our adminiſtration of the Lord Supper in both kinds of bread and wine, is according to the Doctrine, practice, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, of our Sauiour Chriſt and of his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Furthermore as by this meanes the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> hath aboliſhed both parts of the Sacrament, ſo hath it peruerted the right end and vſe for which it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted. For that being as hath beene declared, and as it is made knowne to the people in our admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it, to bee a Sacrament, whereby wee celebrate the memory of the death of Chriſt for our ſinnes, to the ſigning and confirming vnto vs our ſpirituall communion with him, to the participation of all his giftes, euen to life euerlaſting:</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath tranſfigured this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34256:28"/>into a ſacrifice propitiatory for the ſinnes of the liuing, and of the dead. And to this end they haue brought into the Church of Chriſt contrary to his word, a Prieſt, and an Altar, that nothing might bee wanting to the offering of their ſacrifice. In which ſacrifice they teach that the Prieſt doth offer Chriſt enery day vnto his Father, as a ſacrifice to take away ſinnes. Of which propitiatory Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice our Sauiour Chriſt, &amp; his Apoſtles haue made no mention at all, but onely of a commemoration of the death of Chriſt, in the celebration whereof, wee magnifie God and our Sauiour, for ſuch vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mercy and goodneſſe, and ſo offer as it were a Sacrifice of thankſgiuing, pleaſing and acceptable to God in Chriſt Ieſus. But of offering a ſacrifice pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory to take away our ſinnes, and that daily, and by the Prieſt, there is no word in the Scripture for it.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe the Scriptures teach directly the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and declare this Doctrine to bee full of errour and Blaſphemy. For the Scriptures teach vs, that there is but one only Sacrifice that taketh away the ſinnes of men, which is that holy Sacrifice which our Sauiour Chriſt offered of himſelfe, that is, of his humane nature aſſumed for that purpoſe, and that by his eternall Spirit, and that alſo once for all,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.14.25, 26, 28.</note> namely dying vpon the Altar of the croſſe: and by the Sacrifice ſo offered, he hath obtained an euerlaſting redemption. Wherefore to affirme that the Prieſt offereth Chriſt daily in Sacrifice for ſinnes, dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gateth highly from the death of Chriſt, whereby the ſinnes of the faithfull are taken away, as if that had not beene ſufficient; contrary to the whole courſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34256:29"/>of the Scripture, attributing our redemption to his death and blood ſhed vpon the Croſſe. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, This Doctrine highly derogateth from the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the death of Chriſt, in that it teacheth, that Chriſt muſt bee daily offered for ſinne; whereas the Scriptures teach expreſly the contrary, ſaying that Chriſt was to dye but once,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.24, 25. Rom: 5.8.9. Gal. 2.14. Heb. 9.25.</note> and to be offered but once, and ſo to enter into heauen, and not as the High-Prieſt in the Law once euery yeare offered ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and ſo entered into the holy place. For then as the Apoſtle there teacheth he ſhould haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red often ſince the beginning of the world: But now ſaith he, in the end and conſummation of the world, Chriſt was manifeſted to aboliſh ſinne, by the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of himſelfe. Moreouer, it is ſayd, that Chriſt offered his ſacrifice by his eternall Spirit,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.26</note> whereby wee are taught, that it was by the power of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, that his ſacrifice and blood, was of ſo preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ineſtimable and infinite value, as being the bloed of God, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh elſewhere, which redeemed and purchaſed the Church.
<note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> Therefore it is open blaſphemy to affirme, that the Prieſt offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Chriſt vnto his Father a Sacrifice for ſinne, which the Scriptures attributeth to Chriſts eternall Spirit and Godhead.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, many other are the abuſes commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in abuſing this holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, to ſundry other ends, for which Chriſt did neuer ordaine it. For they abuſe it to obtaine bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily health, and proſperous ſucceſſe of voyages at Sea, of battels, of marriage, and ſuch like. They abuſe it to recouer things that are loſt, to the quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Fire, to the calming of Stormes and Tempeſts
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34256:29"/>at Sea, and at Land; to ratifie leagues, to triall of the innocent in Criminall cauſes, and finally to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſoules (as they faine) out of Purgatory.</p>
               <p>For theſe and ſuch like ends, they haue Maſſes ſaid and ſung, and peruert the moſt holy ordinance of Chriſt, to their ſecular and prophane deſires. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, according to the Doctrine of our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles, this Sacrament is with vs to bee adminiſtred, ſo as not onely the Miniſter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone receiue it, but others with him. For ſo our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour deliuered it to his Diſciples, and ſaid, <hi>Take ye, eate, and drinke yee all of this.</hi> Likewiſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the bread of the Lords table, the Communion of the Lords body; and the cuppe of bleſſing, the Communion of his blood: Whereby it is playne, that this Sacrament ought to bee admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in a Congregation of the faithfull and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people, which together with the miniſter ſhould be partakers of the Lords table.</p>
               <p>But contrary to this ordinance of Chriſt are all the priuate Maſſes of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in that the Prieſt alone hauing eaten vp his hoſt (as hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it) and drunke vp his wine, ſendeth the people empty away, after that hee hath bleſt them with the empty cuppe, to the high diſhonour of God, and, the intollerable ſcorne and deriſion of his people. Heere unto is to be added that horrible idolatrie, that is the abominable fruit of the monſtrous errour of Tranſubſtantiation. For from hence came the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and adoration of the wafer-cake, which the Prieſt with his backe toward the people, lifting vp ouer his head, all the people preſent falling downe vpon their knees, and knocking their breaſts religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34256:30"/>worſhip and adore euen with the ſame adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which themſelues acknowledge to bee done to God. And after the Maſſe finiſhed and ended, they relerue the wafer-cake remaining, whereas by the Scripture euery Sacrament, is a Sacrament onely in the lawfull vſe of it, and while that ſacred action bee adminiſtred and finiſhed. For as the water of Baptiſme, after the vſe of it in baptizing ſuch as are to be baptized, is not reſerued; no more ought the Sacramentall bread to be kept and layd vp in ſtore: yet to the eleuation and adoration mentioned, they add alſo this reſeruation of the bread and incloſing it in a pixe, and that alſo for idolatrous vſes.</p>
               <p>For both daily as occaſion requireth in viſitation of the ſicke, they carry this Idoll with pompe throughout the ſtreets, and compell all that meete it, to worſhip and adore it; and once in the yeare, in the day which they haue made feſtiuall for that purpoſe, with great pompe and ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmity they carry it in proceſſion to be worſhipped &amp; adored by the people. Finally whereas our Sauiour Chriſt hath ordained this holy Sacrament, to be adminiſtred in that ſincerity, and ſimplicity, declared in his word; the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> hath deuiſed to adminiſter it in ſuch manner as is fitter for a play vpon a ſtage, or ſome pompous ſolemnity, then for the graue and reuerend adminiſtration of that holy Sacrament. For all fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture belonging to it, is coſtly &amp; ſumptuous, there is muſique to pleaſe the eares, ſweete odors and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes to ſmell, there are to behold whatſoeuer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Images decked with gold and pretious ſtones, and coſtly garments. The Prieſt cloathed richly as <hi>Aaron,</hi> ſtandeth at the Altar ſhining with burning
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34256:30"/>lights, with his attendants in Sylke and fine Linnen, all the people being behind him afarre off. There he playeth many ſtrange parts, ſomtime hee ſtandeth ſtill, ſometime hee walketh a little, one while hee is vpright, another while hee boweth himſelfe; hee ſeemeth to bee aſleepe and to awake againe, hee turneth altogether, and halfe round; his armes are ſometimes ſpread abroad, ſometimes drawne in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; ſometimes lift vp, and ſometime caſt downe: his fingers are ſtill occupied in making croſſes, hee ſoftly murmureth ſomething with himſelfe, and he whiſpereth ouer the bread and the cuppe; at the laſt when hee hath done playing, hee eateth vp his hoſt, and drinketh vp his wine with great care that hee leaueth not a droppe. Then hauing waſhed after his banquet, hee turneth himſelfe to the people, and bleſſing them with the empty cuppe, biddeth them depart. What can bee more vnlike the ſacred admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Lords Supper, then this hiſtrioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſeruice of an Idoll of Bread, which they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and eate vp?</p>
               <p>Wherewith if our adminiſtration of this holy Sacrament bee compared, and either of them with the Lords inſtitution, it will manifeſtly appeare that their Maſſe hath no reſemblance with the Lords Supper, and that for moſt iuſt and neceſſary cauſes, the manifold abuſes of it are reformed in our Church. It will alſo appeare that the communion celebrated in our Churches: Firſt, with declaration of the Doctrine, ſigned by it in the vulgar tongue. Secondly, in both kinds of bread and wine. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in commemoration of the death of Chriſt, with due prayles and prayers annexed thereunto. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34256:31"/>in that it is truely a Communion, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated with the Aſſembly of Gods people. Fiftly, It is freed from Popiſh tranſubſtantiation, eleuation, adoration, reſeruation, and Pompous car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying abroad in the ſtreets, Sacrifices, Sacrificer, and Altar, and from many ſuch other like errours, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions, Idolatries, Blaſphemies, and ridiculous ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, as haue corrupted, peruerted, and tranſfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into an abhominable Idoll the moſt holy, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and comfortable ordinance and Sacrament of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. And thus farre of the word and Sacraments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of Prayers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow it followeth to ſpeake of the Prayers of our Church in <hi>England:</hi> In all which theſe two moſt neceſſary and excellent poynts are moſt worthy to bee conſidered. Firſt, that all our prayers are made to God onely; and Secondly that they are all made by the onely medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Ieſus Chriſt. Of which two poynts the former is ſuch as our Sauiour Chriſt, and all the Prophets and Apoſtles beare witneſſe vnto it.</p>
               <p>For, Firſt, there is not in them all, any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, promiſe, or example for Prayer to bee made to any other. Secondly, All the commandements, promiſes and examples concerning prayer, doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly direct vs to make our prayers vnto God.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.14.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the day of trouble</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>Thou ſhalt
<pb facs="tcp:34256:31"/>call vpon mee, and I will heare thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie mee:
<note place="margin">Math. 6.9. Luk. 11.2.9.12, 13. Math 7.11.</note> When you pray</hi> (Saith our Sauiour) <hi>Pray yee thus. Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>Your heauenly Father will giue good things to theſe that aske him.</hi> The reaſon hereof is, becauſe as the Apoſtle teacheth,
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Euery good grace and perfect guift proceedeth from abone, euen from the Father of lights.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this being the honor of God, hee endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not that it ſhould be giuen to any other, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it is ſayd, <hi>I will not giue my glory to Idols,
<note place="margin">Eſay, 42.8.</note> nor my honor to any other.</hi> And in the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement hee calleth himſelfe a Iealous God,
<note place="margin">Exo. 205.</note> and ſuch as communicate his honor with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hee calleth his enimies, and ſuch as hate him, and threatneth to puniſh their ſinne in themſelues, and in their third and fourth generations that ſhall come after them. So highly doth it diſpleaſe God, that Prayer ſhould bee made to any other, not onely for the ſpace of few dayes, according to the edict of <hi>Darius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 6.7.8.9.10.</note> but for any part of the whole time of our life. For ſuch is the prohibition of God, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in all the Scriptures, and the threatning of his diſpleaſure, and Indignation, which is more to bee feared without all compariſon then all the dennes of Lyons. Therefore it is playne, that whereas in <hi>England</hi> all our Prayers in diuine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, are directed and made to God onely, that our Religion herein is that which the Scriptures teach vs, and namely which the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and the Lord himſelfe hath taught and deliuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>In like manner, whereas all our Prayers are made
<pb facs="tcp:34256:32"/>in the onely mediation of Ieſus Chriſt, wee are thus taught to pray by the Scripture, euen by Chriſt himſelfe and his Apoſtles. For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Whatſoeuer yee ſhall aske of the Father in my name,
<note place="margin">Iohn 14.13. Chap. 15.16. Chap. 16.23.24. 1 Iohn 2.1.2.</note> will be giuen you.</hi> Likewiſe the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> teacheth vs, <hi>that the aduocate wee haue with the Father is Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, who is alſo the propitiation for our ſins.</hi> Likewiſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, that this is a principall part of the honour of his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and that hee liueth now for euer (as hee was ordained a Prieſt for euer after the order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech</hi>) that hee might make interceſſion for vs.
<note place="margin">Heb. 7.24, 25</note> Moreouer, hee is ſaid to haue entred into the holyeſt place of the Sanctuary,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.12.</note> that is, into heauen by his owne blood,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.24.25.</note> hauing obtained euerlaſting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for vs, Whereby it is declared, that after that by the offering of himſelfe once, hee had redeemed his people, hee entred into heauen it ſelfe that hee may now appeare for vs before the face of God. Which doctrine doth manifeſtly teach vs, that to make interceſſion for vs, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, vs and our Prayers grace and fauour with God for euer, is the proper and peculiar honor of our Sauiour Chriſt, and without high treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his dignity cannot bee communicated with any other. For there is one onely high Prieſt of the New Teſtament, which is Ieſus Chriſt; and therefore there can bee no other, neither can that office bee made common to him with any other, without high derogation to his Prieſthood. Beſide, that onely high Prieſt of the New Teſtament, is made Prieſt of the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> of whoſe order none can bee, but hee that is without Father
<pb facs="tcp:34256:32"/>and Mother and genealogie, and therefore no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man whatſoeuer but hee that is alſo God. Againe, he that is a Prieſt of the order of <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeck,</hi> muſt haue beene made Prieſt by the oath of God; but this agreeth onely to Chriſt, as it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Heb 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue ſworne and will not repent, that thou art a Prieſt for euer, after the order of Melchiſedeck</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further, whoſoeuer is a Prieſt of that order, muſt bee alſo King of the Church,
<note place="margin">Heb. 7.21.</note> as <hi>Melcheſedeck</hi> was a Prieſt, and alſo King of <hi>Salem,</hi> and as his name imported, a King of righteouſneſſe. But this honor cannot without high treaſon againſt the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dignity of Chriſt bee communicated with any creature whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, ſeeing there are two parts and duties belonging to this Prieſthood, and that the one which is to bee the aduocate that maketh ſuite and interceſſion for the Church, and the other to offer himſelfe to make propitiation for our ſinnes; and that none can bee our aduocate, but hee that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth propitiation for vs, it is playne, that wee can haue no other aduocate but the ſame that dyed for vs. And that this is ſo, may bee proued many wayes. The Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee haue an aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the Father, which is Ieſus Chriſt the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, who is the propitiation for our ſinnes.</hi> By which words, it appeareth to appertaine to one and the ſame perſon to bee the aduocate, and to make propitiation and ſatisfaction for our ſinnes. But there is no creature that can make ſatisfaction for our ſinnes, this being of all parts confeſſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long onely to Chriſt Ieſus. Therefore alſo to bee aduocate and interceſſor, for the Church cannot
<pb facs="tcp:34256:33"/>belong to any creature, either man or Angell, but is proper to Ieſus Chriſt. And if any ſhould deny it to bee proper to the perſon of Chriſt, to make propitiation for our ſinnes, it may bee proued by this that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Act. 10.28.</note> 
                  <hi>That God redeemed the Church by his blood;</hi> ſo calling it the blood of God, wherewith the Church is redeemed, becauſe in the ſame perſon of Ieſus Chriſt, are both the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, whoſe blood was ſhed; and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, which made it of ineſtimable prize and value, to bee effectuall to redeeme the Church. But the blood of no other Perſon can bee called the blood of God, therefore no other perſon can make ſatisfaction for ſinne and reconcile vs vnto God.</p>
               <p>Now touching the interceſſion of Chriſt, it is to be conſidered, that it is by the ſame his owne blood, that he entred into heauen (as the High-Prieſt entred into the holyeſt place of the Sanctuary with ſtrange blood) there to appeare alwayes in the preſence of God as our aduocate, and to make interceſſion for vs. Which being the blood of God (as hath bene declared) whereby he entered into heauen, and that becauſe hee is as it were ſprinkled with that moſt precious blood of ineſtimable value, hee is worthy to obtaine fauour for all his redeemed, and hearing for all their Prayers; It is plaine heereby, that no other Perſon whatſoeuer can bee our inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, becauſe they are not entered by that blood into heauen, nor cannot preſent themſelues ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with it before the preſence of God, thereby to obtaine fauour with him for vs and our Prayers. Finally, that Ieſus Chriſt and no other perſon can
<pb facs="tcp:34256:33"/>bee our interceſſor with God, is proued by this; that it behooueth him that ſhould preſent our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to know all the prayers of the Church: But this none other but God knoweth, for this is a part of the high ſtile proper to God, <hi>That he knoweth the heart.</hi> Therefore no other perſon but Ieſus Chriſt can bee interceſſor,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.21. 2 Chro. 6.30. Act. 1.24. Act. 15.8. Rom. 8.15. Gal. 9.6, Rom. 8.26.</note> and to whom elſe can it agree but to him whoſe Spirit teacheth vs to call <hi>Abba Father,</hi> and who onely vnderſtandeth the meaning of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that teacheth vs to pray with vnſpeakable gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, as being his owne Spirit that ſtireth vp thoſe ſighes in the faithfull? By all which reaſons it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that no perſon amongſt all creatures can bee our interceſſor, to offer our prayers to God, and by whom wee are to offer them; but on the contrary, that it is onely by the perſon of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thus both theſe poynts in the prayers of our Church in <hi>England</hi> are ſhewed to bee grounded in the Doctrine of Chriſt, and of his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Now it followeth, to ſhew that contrary to this Doctrine of Chriſt and of his Apoſtles, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> maketh prayers to other then to God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by other Mediators and interceſſors, then by the onely Mediator and interceſſor Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, who is the propitiation for our ſinnes; which is firſt to bee ſhewed.</p>
               <p>Now if the liturgie vſed in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> bee compared with the diuine Seruice in <hi>England</hi> in theſe two principall poynts concerning Prayer, it will bee cleare to all that haue eyes to ſee, that as our practiſe in them is directly that which was taught by our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles, ſo that which is vſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:34256:34"/>contrary to Chriſts moſt holy doctrine, and that was deliuered by the Prophets and Apoſtles. For touching the former poynt which is that all pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, petitions, requeſts, ſupplications, and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuings, are to bee made and yelded to God onely: In the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> there are many prayers, petitions, and thankſgiuings, that are made and yeelded vnto Creatures, and euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Images and repreſentations of them. They are made protectors and patrons to bee prayed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, for helpe by ſeuerall Countryes, Cittyes, Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, States, orders, profeſſions, artificers, houſes, perſons.</p>
               <p>Their helpe is prayed for ſeuerally according to diuers ſtates of men, Knights, men of ſtudy, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, Lawyers, artificers, as Painters, Shooma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Smithes, Potters. Likewiſe according to ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry occaſions of the liuing Creatures they poſſeſſe diuerſly, as for Geeſe, Sheepe, Horſes, Oxen. They pray alſo to ſundry Patrons, to bee deliuered from ſtormes, and tempeſts, from Earthquakes, Fyres and blaſtings. And in caſe of diuers fickeneſſes they pray to ſundry helpers againſt the Peſtilence, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Toothach, Gout, Falling ſickneſſe and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>In their Letany and Maſſes they pray to Angels, to the Mother of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, to Martyrs, to diuers confeſſors, Biſhops Doctors of the Church, and to Saints of the Popes Cannonizing and ſaynting. In their prayers to them they pray them to ſaue their ſinfull ſoules, to deſtroy their enemies, to heale them of their diſeaſes, to deliuer them from all aduerſities, and all impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:34256:34"/>of Soule and body, at the howre of death to receiue their ſoules, and to bring them to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. An infinite number almoſt of exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of ſuch prayers might be rehearſed, which they make vnto Creatures. And to them likewiſe they offer their thankſgiuing, vowes incenſe, guifts and oblations, yea they ſay the Lords Prayer beginning <hi>Our Father &amp;c.</hi> Before euery picture and Image of them in their Churches or houſes, ſo fulfilling that which was ſayd to the old Idolaters, that they ſay to the block, and to the ſtone, thou haſt begotten me.
<note place="margin">Eſay 44.17: Hab. 2.19.</note> But to the bleſſed Mother of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, they doe more wrong in this kinde then to any of the ſoules of the faithfull that are departed out of this life, for they magnifie her with the names of our Lady, the Queene of Heauen, the Lady of the Angels, the mother of mercy, the hope of the Church, our life, our ſweetneſſe, our hope; ſome of them ſay, that God hath giuen her, the one halfe of his Kingdome, that is, of mercy, and hath reſerued to himſelfe the other which is of iudgment: they ſay alſo vnto her, By right of a mother, commaund thy ſonne: they abuſe the Salutation of the Angell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning in latine with <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> as a prayer vnto her, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to doe her honor with the rehearſing of it, and ordaine that it bee ſayd at a knell of the bell. They vſe Roſaryes in her honor, that is, ſaying <hi>Aues</hi> vpon their beades, &amp; for euery ten of them, one <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſter,</hi> that is in all 55 to a Roſary. Of three ſuch Roſaryes they made a Pſalter for her, wherein ſhold be 150 <hi>Aues</hi> according to the number of the Pſalmes.</p>
               <p>There hath alſo beene made a ſpeciall Letany to her, and a Pſalter wherein throwout all the Pſalmes, the name Lord is turned into Lady, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34256:35"/>is ſpoken to God in all the Pſalmes, is attributed vnto her. But it were endleſſe to rehearſe all the meanes whereby God is robbed of this high p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt of his glory, of Prayers and prayſes, by ſuch as are of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and namely by their pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, canonicall howres, Letanies, Collects, antipho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes, miſſals, and ſuch like parts of their Liturgie, and diuine Seruice.</p>
               <p>This may ſuffice to ſhew how that which was intended, that whereas in our diuine Seruice in <hi>England,</hi> wee offer prayers and thankes vnto God onely according to the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, they offer them to Creatures, paſſing by the Creator bleſſed for euer, Amen. Wherein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, they haue not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to the number of their Citties multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed their Gods, as it is ſayd, <hi>According to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thy Cittyes are thy Gods O Iudah;</hi> but of townes, ſtreets, Churches, Chappels, houſes, perſons, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, and other occaſions, euen to praying to dumbe ſtockes and ſtones, to the aſtoniſhment of heauen and earth, as it is in the Prophet <hi>Ieremy: O yee Heauens,
<note place="margin">Iere. 2.12.13.</note> bee aſtoniſhed at this, bee affrayd and vtterly confounded ſaith the Lord; for my people haue committed two euils, they haue forſaken mee, the fountaine of liuing waters, to dig them pits, that can hold no water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other poynt is like vnto this. For whereas in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, as Chriſt and his Apoſtles haue taught vs, we haue but one God to whom wee pray, and but one Mediator and interceſſor by whom and in whoſe name and merits wee preſent our Prayers to God: So on the contrary part, the
<pb facs="tcp:34256:35"/>Church of <hi>Rome</hi> directly contrary to the doctrine of Chriſt, and of all the Scriptures, prayeth to men and Angels, as hath beene declared; ſo doth it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe offer vp Prayers to God, by the interceſſion of Angels and of men.</p>
               <p>This appeareth in like manner in their Letanies, Miſſalls, Anthemes, Collects and ſundry parts of their Liturgie. For in them they deſire all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Arch-Angels to pray for them, and by name <hi>Gabriel, Michaell, Raphaell.</hi> They deſire the mediation of all the Apoſtles in generall, and of euery out in particular. This petition they make alſo to all the Martyres in common, and to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers by their proper Names; to the Doctors of the Church to Confeſſors, to ſundry Popes, Biſhops, Abbots, and other Canonized Saints, both men, and women, that they would pray for them to God, that by their interceſſion, yea and alſo by their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, they may bee freed from their ſinnes, and the puniſhment due for the ſame, and may obtaine all grace to euerlaſting life. In ſo many ſundry ſorts doe they diſhonor the Sunne of God, and rob him of that high glory and preheminence of his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, which ſtandeth in making interceſſion for his people, in communicating it with ſo many others, to whom it cannot in any ſort belong. For it is hee alone that was made the High Prieſt of the new Teſtament, and that with an oath, and the ſame for euer, for which cauſe alſo his Prieſthood is ſayd to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuch as paſſeth not from his owne perſon to any other.
<note place="margin">Heb. 7.16.17.20.21. Heb, 7.23.24</note> Hee obtained this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to enter into heauen, to make prayer and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for vs by the ſhedding of his moſt pretious
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34256:36"/>blood, by the merrit whereof hee preſenteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe continually in the preſence of God,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.7.12. Ver. 12.14</note> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all grace needfull for his Church; which ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor hauing beene obtained by blood, it cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to Angels which are only ſpirits, &amp; neither haue fleſh nor blood. This blood whereby hee obtained this honor,
<note place="margin">1, Pet. 1.19. Iohn, 1.19.36. Heb, 9.14.</note> is the blood of the Lambe immaculate &amp; vndefiled, without ſpot or blemiſh, that is, of one perfectly innocent and righteous in the ſight of God, But ſuch is not the ſtate of any man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 53.6. Pſal. 143.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee haue all erred and gone aſtray</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Eſay:</hi> And the Propher <hi>Dauid likewiſe, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into Iudgement with thy Seruant (O Lord) for no fleſh ſhall bee iuſtified in thy ſight;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.3. Rom. 3.10.</note> And againe, <hi>There is none that doth good, no not one:</hi> Which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the teſtimony of all the Prophets and Apoſtles: wherefore all men are ſubiect to death by reaſon of ſinne, and are not able to procure fauour for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, how then ſhould they bee mediators and interceſſors to procure fauour for others, who them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſtand in neede to bee ſaued by the interceſſion and merrits of Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
               <p>But if there were any of them righteous, yet the ſhedding of their blood could no more procure fauour for vs with God then the ſhedding of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the ſtreetes. For it is by the blood of God (as ſaith the Apoſtle) whereby the Church is bought and purchaſed,
<note place="margin">A &amp;. 20.26.</note> by which blood as hee made propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for our ſinnes, ſo it is by the ſame blood, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ineſtimable value becauſe of the infinite dignitie of his perſon) by which hee is entered into the preſence of God, to make interceſſion for vs.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:34256:36"/>
               <p> It is therefore of no vſe that is ſaid, that hee is the onely mediator of propitiation but not of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. For as it hath bene ſhewed by theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, hee hath as good right to bee honored with this glory, to bee the onely interceſſor for his Church, as hee hath to bee the onely giuer of all ſatisfaction for our ſinnes. Finally it behooueth that our interceſſor bee God, that hee may know the neceſſities of this people, and vnderſtand their groanes which cannot bee vttered; but this agreeth not to any creature onely, much leſſe to men. Thus then it appeareth in how high degree the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles and derogatory to the honor of God, and of his onely Sonne, in that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are made to any other then to God onely, and that reſting vpon the Prayers and interceſſion of many others and not onely of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Contrary wiſe hereby it may appeare, that our Religion and diuine Seruice in <hi>England,</hi> in theſe two laſt and excellent poynts concerning Prayer, is according to the Doctrine of Chriſt and of his Apoſtles, that wee pray to God onely, and that by the onely mediation of Ieſus Chriſt the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, who is alſo the propitiation for our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Thus it hath beene ſhewed, both in the word whereunto the Sacraments are annexed, and alſo in prayer, in which two parts principally conſiſteth the whole ſeruice of God; that our Religion profeſſed in <hi>England,</hi> is the ſame which was taught by Ieſus Chriſt and by his Apoſtles, which was deſired to be proued; and further that the Liturgie of the Church
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34256:37"/>of <hi>Rome,</hi> in all the poynts heere debated, is directly contrary to the Apoſtolicall Doctrine, and that which was deliuered by the Lord Ieſus himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Which being ſo performed, heere might bee an end of this Treatiſe, but that it is further deſired to bee ſhewed, if any of the Martyres haue giuen te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to that Religion which in <hi>England</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed: For ſatisfaction wherein, here is added that which followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of Martyrs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Artyr, is originally a Greeke word, and ſignifieth in <hi>Engliſh</hi> a witneſſe, which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſignification by an elegancy of ſpeech, is vſed by the Church, to note ſuch as te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie and beare witneſſe of true Religion, and of the right Seruice of God, and of faith in Ieſus Chriſt, euen by the ſuffering of death, rather then to deny the truth of God. So as in this ſence, Martyr is a witneſſe of true Religion, by his ſuffering of death for it.</p>
               <p>Such in the time of the Prophets were <hi>Daniel,</hi> and his three noble kinſmen of the tribe of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 3.20.21.</note> For theſe three rather then they would worſhip <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzars</hi> golden Image, and yeeld to an Idoll the honour due to the onely true God, endured to bee caſt into the furnace of fire. From which though God by miracle deliuered them, yet are they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily accounted Martyrs, for their moſt conſtant reſolution.
<note place="margin">Dan. 6.16.</note> Likewiſe <hi>Daniel,</hi> rather then hee would
<pb facs="tcp:34256:37"/>not yeeld vnto God the honor of prayer, endured to bee caſt into the denne of Lyons for his noble Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
               <p>In the new Teſtament our Sauiour ſpeaking of Martyrdome, ſaith,
<note place="margin">Math. 5.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are yee when men perſecute you for righteouſneſſe, and for my ſake.</hi> And fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warning his Diſciples of ſuch Perſecution, ſaith, <hi>You ſhall beare witneſſe of mee,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 15.27. Iohn. 16.2.</note> and they will put you out of their ſynagogue; and whoſoeuer ſhall kill you ſhall thinke hee doth God good ſeruice.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>If any man ſuffer becauſe hee is a Chriſtian,
<note place="margin">1, Pet, 4.16.</note> let him not hee aſhawed, let him rather glorifie God on this behalfe.</hi> Thus alſo wrighteth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> alledging it out of the <hi>Pſalmes:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.22. Rom. 8.36.</note> For thy ſake are wee put to death all the day long, wee are accounted as ſheepe for the ſlaughter.</hi> By theſe and many other like teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies it appeareth, that a true Martyr dyeth for no other cauſe, but for a good, iuſt, and holy cauſe, and namely, for witneſſe bearing to true Religion; as for refuſing to worſhip Idols, and for profeſſing himſelfe a Chriſtian, and one that honoreth Chriſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Doctrine of the Goſpel that hee taught, and profeſſeth to belieue to bee ſaued by him.</p>
               <p>Which being thus proued, by theſe generall te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, ſhall bee likewiſe confirmed by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of ſuch true Martyrs, to the end that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may appeare, that whoſoeuer are to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to haue beene true Martyrs, haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for earing witneſſe to ſome principall doctrine of the ſame Religion, that together with all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, is profeſſed at this day in <hi>England,</hi> and not for maintenance of any of the errors or falſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34256:38"/>worſhips maintained by the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> and wherein they being fallen away from the truth of the Goſpel, diſſent from many nations of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world.</p>
               <p>They challenge indeed to themſelues, that all the Martyrs that dyed in the Primitiue Church, dyed for their Religion. But it is not to bee ſhewed that they dyed for that Corruption of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that is properly called Popery, becauſe it hath beene and is ſtill maintained by the authority of Popes; but onely for refuſing to worſhip Idols, &amp; for profeſſing to beleeue in God, and in Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour.</p>
               <p>Which being the holy faith now profeſſed in <hi>England,</hi> and in many other nations of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that agree with vs therein, it will appeare that all the Martyrs of the primitiue Church dyed for the maintenance of that Seruice of God, and for that faith of Chriſt, which is now profeſſed in <hi>England,</hi> which is the other part that is defired to be proued.</p>
               <p>Now for the proofe let vs firſt conſider of the Martyrs recorded in the new Teſtament. Whereof the firſt that obtained the Crowne of Martyrdome was <hi>Steuen,</hi> who had beene one of the Seuen Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons of the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> Of him it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that hee was ſtoned to death in a fury of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> after that hee had giuen notable teſtimony to Ieſus Chriſt. Firſt, by his great ſignes and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that hee did. Secondly, his ſo wiſe and Zealous reaſoning with men ofthe Synagogues and ſchools of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> of diuers nations that were in <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> as they were not able to withſtand the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:34256:38"/>and ſpirit wherewith hee ſpake. Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Act. 6.10. Act. 7, 2, &amp;c. V. 52. V. 55: V. 59</note> by his notable Apologie which hee made for himſelfe before the High-Prieſt, and the whole Conſiſtory, his face ſhining as an Angel, concluding it with charging their Fathers to haue ſlayne the Prophets, which had foreſhewed the comming of Chriſt, and themſelues to haue murdered Chriſt, that iuſt and righteous Perſon. Fourthly, by his conſtant teſtimony that hee beheld the heauens open, and the Sonne of man ſtanding at the right hand of God. Finally by his dying in the inuocation of the name of the Lord Ieſus.</p>
               <p>By all which reaſons it is plaine, that <hi>Steuen</hi> dyed, for no other cauſe then onely for profeſſing Ieſus Chriſt to bee the Sonne of God, and the Sauiour whom God had promiſed to ſend for the ſaluation of his people; and this faith our Church in <hi>England</hi> by Gods mercy doth conſtantly profeſſe, with all that call vpon the name of the Lord Ieſus, and houldeth it moſt honorable to dye forbearring wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to that moſt holy faith. Which being ſo, it is cleare that <hi>Steuen,</hi> whoſe head firſt had the honor to weare the Crowne of Martyrdome, dyed for that faith which is at this day profeſſed in <hi>England,</hi> &amp; not for the Maſſe, nor the Popes Supremacy, nor any other Popiſh Corruption of Chriſtian faith whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>The like is to bee ſayd of the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> whom <hi>Herod</hi> ſlew with the ſword, as it appeareth by that it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Act. 12.1.2.3.</note> that <hi>Herod</hi> vexed certaine of the Church, and that hee ſaw, that the killing of <hi>Iames</hi> had pleaſed the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who were the enimies of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34256:39"/>Chriſt, and by apprehending and committing of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in like ſort.</p>
               <p>In the Acts of the Apoſtles, the like cauſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth of all the perſecution both of the Diſciples and of the Apoſtles. Wherefore vpon occaſion the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth ſaying, I am ready not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee bound,
<note place="margin">Act. 21.13.</note> but alſo to dye at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for the name of the Lord Ieſus. In the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> the like teſtimony is giuen of <hi>Antipas,</hi> where it is written; <hi>I know thy workes,
<note place="margin">Reue. 2.13.</note> and where thou dwelleſt, namely where Sathans throne is; I know that thou holdeſt my name, and haſt not denied my faith, no not in the dayes wherein Antipas my faithfull Martyr was ſlayne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, where Sathan dwelleth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of other Chriſtian Martyrs whoſe names are not mentioned in the Scriptures, the like appeareth both by the prophecies and performances of their ſufferings. In the ſecond of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the 10 verſe, <hi>Feare nothing of that thou art to ſuffer; Behold the Diuell will cast ſome of you into priſon that yee may bee tryed, and yee ſhall haue affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for ten dayes: Bee faithfull vnto the death, and I will giue thee the Crowne of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſixt Chapter, verſe the ninth, where the firſt ſeale was opened, it is ſayd: <hi>I ſaw vnder the Altar the ſoules of thoſe which had beene ſlayne for the word of God, and for the teſtimony which they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</hi> After to them crying to God to reuenge their blood, it is in the eleuenth verſe anſwered, <hi>That they ſhould reſt yet a little time vntill their fellow ſeruants, &amp; their brethren might bee fulfilled, which were to bee ſlayne as well as they.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Chapter cleauenth, from the third verſe to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:34256:39"/>the twelfth, is foreſhewed the Martyrdome of the two Witneſſes which bare witneſſe to the Goſpell of Chriſt, <hi>for the ſpace of</hi> 1260 <hi>dayes.</hi> Finally in Chap 20 verſe 4. it is ſaid, <hi>I ſaw the ſoules of thoſe which had beene ſmitten with the axe for the teſtimony of Ieſus and for the word of God, and which haue not worſhipped the beaſt nor the Image of the beaſt, nor haue the marke vpon their foreheads, or in their hands; and they ſhall liue and reigne with Chriſt a thouſand yeares.</hi> Theſe are the Prophecies that make mention of Chriſtian Martyrs, by all which places and the comparing them one with another it may euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, that all ſuch Martyrs were to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Lord Ieſus Chriſt vnto death, and to ſuffer not for any tradition or for any ordinance of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but for the word of God, and for refuſing to become Idolaters, and to take the marke of the beaſt in their foreheads or in their hands.</p>
               <p>Now the performance of theſe prophecies that haue beene fulfilled vnto this time, doe likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that the Chriſtian Martyrs, which haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered hitherto haue ſuffered death for profeſſing that they worſhipped onely the true God, that had made heauen &amp; earth; &amp; his onely begotten Sonne Ieſus Chriſt: and refuſed to worſhip the Pagan Emperours Idols, and the Idols of the heathen, that liued in any part of the Romane Empire. The cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and vndoubted truth hereof, is to bee iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Apologeticall and other writings of the ancient Fathers, by the hiſtory of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> &amp; other writers of Eccleſiaſticall ſtory &amp; namely of Martyrs; likewiſe by <hi>Aurelius Prudentius</hi> in his booke of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34256:40"/>Crownes of Martyrs, and other of like argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>By the teſtimony of theſe writers it appeareth for the tyme of the ten great and cruell perſecutions of the <hi>Romane</hi> Emperours, while they were yet hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, euen to the reigne of <hi>Conſtantiue</hi> the Great, which was the ſpace of aboue 300 yeares, and namely, in the laſt tenne yeeres perſecutions, vnder the fiue laſt heathen Emperours, which time is thought to bee forſhewed by the mention of tenne dayes ſpoken in the 2 Chap. of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> the 10 verſe: For by all theſe it is plentifully teſtified, that the Chriſtians were put to death for no other cauſe, but for profeſſing themſelues to bee Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and refuſing to worſhip the Idols of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
               <p>The ſame is confirmed alſo by forraigne and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then writers, and namely, by the edicts and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations of Emperors, by the commandements of their officers in their ſeuerall Prouinces, by their proceeding in Iudgment, the voyce of the cryer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claming, that they which ſuffered death, profeſſed themſelues to bee Chriſtians, by a writing which was written in a table of ſuch their profeſſion, which was borne before the Martyrs; and finally, by the ſentences of their Iudges, for ſuch cauſe onely, adiuding them to ſuffer diuers ſundry kindes of exquiſite torments and cruell deaths. To proue this by the particular report of all the Martyrs that ſuffered in that time to the reigne of the Great <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine,</hi> would bee two long. But wee may take a few for example amongſt thoſe that are reported to ſuffer Martyrdome in that time. Heere may bee
<pb facs="tcp:34256:40"/>remembred <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> Paſtor of the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> a tree that bare much fruite according to his name, and like the Date, or Almond tree, which the more it is preſſed, is the more fruitefull. For of him it is written, that after horrible threatnings of wild beaſts and of fire, growing in conſtancy, and perſeuering ſtedfaſtly, in profeſſing himſelfe to bee a Chriſtian, and refuſing to worſhip the Idols of the heathen, the Cryer by commandement proclaimed and cryed thrice, <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carpus</hi> hath confeſſed himſelfe to bee a Chriſtian: Likewiſe the people cryed out vpon him, This is that Teacher of <hi>Aſia,</hi> the Father of the Chriſtians, the ouerthrower of our gods, which hath taught ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that our gods are not to bee worſhipped. For theſe cauſes <hi>Polycarpus</hi> dyed as a faithfull ſeruant of Chriſt, whom hee ſayd hee had ſerued 86 yeares, and hauing found him alwayes his good maſter and gracious Lord, hee would not now deny him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Attalus,</hi> another Martyr, was lead about the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phitheater, and a table borne before him, wherein it was written, This is <hi>Attalus</hi> the Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>It is written of one <hi>Saphyra</hi> a virgin of <hi>Antioch,</hi> that as a faire <hi>Saphyre,</hi> a Iemme, a Iewell, of great price, carying hir holy profeſſion without any ſtaine; being commanded to ſacrifice to the gods of the heathen, ſhee graciouſly anſwered that ſhee was a Chriſtian, and worſhipped almighty God, who had created all things; and that the gods of the <hi>Gentils</hi> were no gods, but diuels; for which worthy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſhee was beheadded.</p>
               <p>Happy <hi>Faelicitas</hi> according to hir name, a matrone and widdow of <hi>Rome,</hi> the mother of ſeauen chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb facs="tcp:34256:41"/>was accuſed to the Emperour <hi>Antoninus,</hi> by the prieſts of the Idols, that ſhe worſhipped not their gods, but alſo perſwaded others, from doing them honor. Shee was exhorted to ſpare hir ſelfe, and to returne to the old <hi>Romane</hi> Religion, and to forſake the new doctrine of the Chriſtians, and to teſtifie the ſame by the offering of Sacrifice: But ſhee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly profeſſed that ſhee was willing to dye for the faith of Chriſt. After, being exhorted to ſpare hir children, and to perſwade them, to redeeme and ſaue their liues by ſacrificing, ſhee anſwered the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, Thy mercy is impietie, and thy exhortation cruelty. For if my ſonnes ſhould ſacrifice to Idols, they ſhould not ſaue their liues, but caſt themſelues into hell fire. Then turning to hir Children ſhee ſaid, My deareſt ſonnes, perſeuere in the faith, and confeſſion of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, hee expecteth you with all his Saints; fight for your ſoules, and ſhew your ſelues faithfull in the loue of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thus for worſhipping of Chriſt, and refuſing to worſhip Idols, this happy mother, hauing ſeene hir ſeuen ſonnes firſt ſlayne with ſundry deaths, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeauen times in them, at the laſt was alſo crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Martyrdome and receiued to euerlaſting felicity.</p>
               <p>Theſe few examples of almoſt an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, may ſuffice to ſhew, that the Martyrs which ſuffered vnder the heathen <hi>Romaine</hi> Enperours, to the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, which was 300 yeares and more, ſuffered all for profeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to bee Chriſtians, and refuſing to worſhip the Idols of the heathen <hi>Romaine</hi> Emperours. Which
<pb facs="tcp:34256:41"/>being thus declared, hereby is that proued (for the firſt 300 yeares after Chriſt) which was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that is, that the Martyrs of the Primitiue Church dyed for that faith, which the Church of <hi>England,</hi> together with all the reformed Churches of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiandome doe profeſſe. For both theſe are in our Church ſo profeſſed, as wee hold it moſt honorable to dye in maintenance of the faith of Chriſt, and refuſing to worſhip any Idols, either of old <hi>Rome</hi> that worſhipped the Images of heathen men; or of new <hi>Rome,</hi> that adoreth the Images of Chriſtian men. For though the difference of a heathen, and of a Chriſtian man, bee exceeding great; yet in worſhipping of them both religiouſly, and much more in ſo worſhipping their Images, there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, but ſuch Images are Idols alike, and the worſhippers of them are in like ſort Idolaters. But this diſputation belongeth to another place.</p>
               <p>That which is heere to bee debated is, that ſeing our Church in <hi>England</hi> profeſſeth the faith of Chriſt, and abhorreth the Idols of the heathen, as all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches doe; that all the Martyrs of the Primitiue Church, for the firſt three hundreth yeres after Chriſt, dyed for the ſame faith and Religion, which is now profeſſed in <hi>England.</hi> After the time that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great had preuailed againſt his enimies the heathen Princes which were partakers with him in the Empire, the perſecution of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the former manner ceaſſed in all the <hi>Romaine</hi> Empire, excepting the ſhort time of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata; for notwithſtanding that there were grieuous troubles which the true Chriſtians ſuffered alſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, eſpecially by the <hi>Arrians,</hi> and alſo by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:34256:42"/>heretickes and ſchiſmatickes in their ſundry Countries, yet was there not any vniuerſall perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto death in any degree like the former, for the cauſes aboue mentioned, or by the heathen.</p>
               <p>Within the Church there aroſe indeede great troubles generally by the authority of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, that fauoured the hereſy of <hi>Arius,</hi> and by the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops, and other of that hereſy, ſoliciting authority with all importunacy againſt <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and other that maintained the ſound Orthodoxe, and holy faith of the Godhead of Chriſt of one and the ſame ſubſtance with the Father: In which worthy cauſe, whatſoeuer was ſuffered by any, and namely by <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> worthy to bee immortall, and to haue his name preſerued for euer in the Church with high regard and honour, they and <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> ſuffered for that faith that is alſo profeſſed by all reformed Churches, and namely by our Church in <hi>England,</hi> as may appeare by <hi>Athanaſius</hi> Creede, or confeſſion of faith ſet downe in our booke of common prayer, &amp; appoynted by publique autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be openly read in all our Churches.</p>
               <p>Other vniuerſall perſecutions for any matter of Chriſtian faith wee reade of none. And as for ſuch particular troubles as were r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſed in the Church, about any hereſy condemned by any of the foure firſt generall Councels, whatſoeuer thoſe Councels decreed againſt ſuch hereſies, is receiued and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by our Church in <hi>England.</hi> Thus it is proued that all the Martyrs of the Primitiue Church ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for our Religion that is now profeſſed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in all ages whatſoeuer, true and right Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs
<pb facs="tcp:34256:42"/>there haue beene, that is, which ſuffered death for bearing witneſſe to the word of God and to any part of Chriſtian Religion, deliuered by Ieſus Chriſt and by his holy Apoſtles (for it is the cauſe and not the puniſhment onely that maketh a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr) they dyed all for ſome Article or other of the Religion which is profeſſed in <hi>England.</hi> And of this ſort, for ſome laterages, eſpecially in this wherein wee liue, the barbarous Cruelty of the <hi>Romane</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques hath beene ſuch, as in this age, both <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in ſome former times, and eſpecially in the reigne of Queene Mary, and many other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and countries of Chriſtendome, haue flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Chriſtian blood that hath bene ſhed by them. They boaſt indeed of Martyrs that haue dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the defence of their Religion; for which if our Chriſtian Kings and States that haue reſtored the ſincerity of Chriſtian Religion, had made lawes for that purpoſe, and put them in execution vpon ſome turbulent Perſons obſtinately ſeeking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue vs of the true worſhip of God, and to bring vs back againe to the blindneſſe, and ignorance, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions and will worſhips, errours and hereſies, Idolatries and blaſphemies of the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> who could iuſtly reproue ſuch proceedings? But it will bee hard to ſhew that our Chriſtian Princes and States haue yet hitherto ſo proceeded.</p>
               <p>Poſſibly in the warres, and in the rage of battell, and in the fury of victory, ſome outrages may haue bene committed, which we do not iuſtifie. But that in time of peace when lawes might be obeyed, &amp; the Iudges ſit quietly vpon their benches, it will not be eaſy to ſhew that there hath bin any ſuch courſe.
<pb facs="tcp:34256:43"/>Their ſhameleſſe Legendaries report indeed, that we haue put men into Beares skinnes, and ſet dogges to worry them. But they that wrote ſuch things, had neither truth, nor modeſty in ſo writing.</p>
               <p>They complaine much alſo of ſome Ieſuits, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries, and other <hi>Romane</hi> Catholiques, adiudged vnto death in this Land. And it is true, that ſome ſuch haue beene executed, but not any, ſimply for any matter of Religion and diuine Seruice, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Fellonies, and Treaſons, and that ſome ſuch as the like were neuer heard of in any age; or for ſuch erronious, and hereticall poynts of Doctrine as directly impugneth the Soueraignty of the State, and inforced a neceſſity of ſuch Lawes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of them vpon ſome notorious Offendors, and ſeditious practiſers to ſeduce the ſubiects from their allegeance. But this is cleared in many other places, and heere it may ſuffice to ſhew, that which hath beene proued, That the Martyrs of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church dyed for that truth which is now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in <hi>England.</hi> Which hauing beene thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by this Treatiſe, there hath beene performed whatſoeuer is deſired. Which God grant may be of as good vſe to ſuch as haue deſired it: as the writer from his ſoule doth pray God may vouchſafe them.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
